<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>zacblanco.github.io</title>
    <description>A simple tech blog to keepp you updated on my projects and for interesting  tips tricks and hacks.
</description>
    <link>http://zacblanco.github.io//</link>
    <atom:link href="http://zacblanco.github.io//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 11 Mar 2015 01:55:17 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 11 Mar 2015 01:55:17 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Building a Site with Jekyll</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;So I when I first started trying to make a blog I didn’t realize how difficult it would actually be to find something that worked. No other free platform contained the features that I wanted. And as a college student we should know that, free = good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; is no perfect solution, but it does provide a host of features and is much more open than any other option I could find, which is why I opted to switch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a quick intro, Jekyll straight out of the box really isn’t anything special. Basically it takes some text that you write up for your posts and converts them into some static html files that can be served to a user.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Posts are written in &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Markdown&quot;&gt;Markdown&lt;/a&gt; which is a really handy markup language. Great for writing posts, but it does have a bit of a learning curve and takes some time to get used to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another great thing about using Jekyll is that there’s quite a bit of resources, and its open source! It’s very flexible, you can use plugins, create new themes, and add commenting features. This list just goes on!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creating a site from scratch with Jekyll is definitely not for the faint-hearted. If you’re willing to put the time and effort in you can come out with a blog customized to your very liking including only the features you would like. It’s a very hands-on get-dirty-with-the-code project, but it’s a lot of fun and you might learn a few things along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of this post I’ll be showing you how exactly to install and run Jekyll to &lt;em&gt;quickly&lt;/em&gt; create your own static website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;prerequisites&quot;&gt;Prerequisites&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;please-download-ruby-first-then-rubygems&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please download ruby first, then RubyGems&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re going to need &lt;strong&gt;ruby&lt;/strong&gt; installed on your machine. If you dont have ruby installed &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ruby-lang.org/en/downloads/&quot;&gt;you can get it here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re also going to have to install &lt;a href=&quot;https://rubygems.org/pages/download&quot;&gt;RubyGems&lt;/a&gt;. It’s package manager for ruby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I’m going to assume you know how to install these or already have them on your system. Follow the documentation provided online or do a quick google search if you’re having any trouble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve got them both installed, open up a command terminal and try this command&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;~ user$ ruby --version
~ user$ gem --version
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If everything works correctly you should get some type of outputs similar to this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;ruby 2.0.0p481 (2014-05-08 revision 45883) [universal.x86_64-darwin14]
2.0.14
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Great! now we have the two essentials installed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;getting-jekyll&quot;&gt;Getting Jekyll&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a valid internet connection and a command terminal, use the following commands to install Jekyll on your machine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;~ user$ sudo gem install jekyll
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check now that you have the latest version of Jekyll installed by using&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;~ user$ jekyll --version
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;creating-your-first-site&quot;&gt;Creating your first site&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s where things start getting fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using your terminal, navigate to the chosen directory on your filesystem where you would like to keep your code, site, and any other files &lt;em&gt;(Preferably a location where you might keep some repositories)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assuming you’ve already navigated there perform the following&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;~/location/ user$ jekyll new &amp;lt;site-name&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or if you’d like to have jekyll generate the files in the folder you’re currently located in&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;~/site-name/ user$ jekyll new .
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now if you use ls command or view that directory you just created inside a file manager you should see something similar to the following&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;_config.yml	_layouts    _sass	css		index.html
_includes	_posts		about.md	feed.xml
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;configyml&quot;&gt;_config.yml&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This file is where we store some sitewide variables, like author name, baseurl, twitter and GitHub handles, etc. Edit the variables in here as you like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;posts&quot;&gt;_posts&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where you’re going to write posts in the Markdown syntax. I suggest an editor than can support previews of Markdown. Personally I use &lt;a href=&quot;http://brackets.io&quot;&gt;Adobe Brackets&lt;/a&gt; with the Markdown plugin to preview. More on all of this later&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;aboutmd&quot;&gt;about.md&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a markdown file you can edit to change the “About” page on your site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;includes-layouts-sass-css&quot;&gt;_includes, _layouts, _sass, css&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are all other places where you can change configurations and views of your site. The layout and css can all be found under these places. We’re not really going to edit those right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;making-your-first-post&quot;&gt;Making your first post&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lets navigate to our folder and create a new post. Create a new file and name is something following the scheme: &lt;code&gt;YYYY-MM-DD-your-title.md&lt;/code&gt;. Open this new file in a text editor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inside we’re going to put:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;---
layout: post
title: Hello World!
---

# Howdy there partner
Congratulations! You&#39;ve made it to[site](site.url)

We&#39;re ust getting started here.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now save your document and return to the terminal that has navigated inside of your site’s directory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;building-the-site&quot;&gt;Building the Site&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Run the following command&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;~/location/ user$ jekyll build
~/location/ user$ jekyll serve
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leave the terminal open. Open up a new tab in your browser of choice and navigate to &lt;code&gt;http://localhost:4000&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should see a home page with a link to Jekyll’s default page for new sites, and your own post we just wrote!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Click on the post to make sure it works there. If it does, congratulations! you’ve made your first blog post using Jekyll&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s tons more you can do with themes, pages, and other sweet customizations for your shiny new blog, but I’ll go into those at a later date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now, play around with Jekyll and get a feel for the software. It’s something interesting that I’ve never encountered before and is definitely worth a try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy blogging!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://zacblanco.github.io//none</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://zacblanco.github.io//none</guid>
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
        <category>hyde</category>
        
        <category>site</category>
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
        <category>markdown</category>
        
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
        <category>site</category>
        
        <category>markdown</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Blog transfer</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;css-full-post-content js-full-post-content&quot;&gt;
Since I&#39;m pretty new to blogging I haven&#39;t found the platform yet that I like best. I decided blogger was a little too plain and wordpress had some better layouts but didn&#39;t give me enough control, so I&#39;ve decided to move to jekyll hosting using github pages.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I won&#39;t be posting here any longer. Please direct all traffic to &lt;a href=&quot;http://zacblanco.github.io/&quot;&gt;zacblanco.github.io&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;EDIT:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I just want to add my previous post about an updated site-- well. Now that I&#39;m using Jekyll I won&#39;t be able to keep that as the landing page. You can still find it and view-source &lt;a href=&quot;http://zacblanco.github.io/s-old/index.html&quot;&gt;zacblanco.github.io/s-old/index.html&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 09 Mar 2015 17:50:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://zacblanco.github.io//2015/03/blog-transfer.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://zacblanco.github.io//2015/03/blog-transfer.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Updated Site</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;css-full-post-content js-full-post-content&quot;&gt;
So I just wanted to let you guys know that I&#39;ve updated my GitHub pages site. Because I like learning and building things form scratch to learn how everything is put together I built my site from the ground up and learned a few things along the way.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I was inspired to do this redesign after I came across flexbox. A CSS display property that I had not previously known of. It makes a lot of resizing and overall site layout much easier. I was inspired to rebuild my site using this.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The great thing is that flexbox is easy. It just works. and It&#39;s trivial to center things in your screen and resize the browser causing them to flow onto other line. It really is a great tool. The one caveat is that it doesn&#39;t have great browser support.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I&#39;ve currently tested on the most updated versions of the major browsers (IE, Chrome, Firefox, Safari) and so far Chrome and Firefox render the page properly. Unfortunately however, Safari definitely does not render the page properly. Most older browsers don&#39;t Although I&#39;m not too worried about this. Even with improper display the page is still navigable. IE11 surprisingly does. Even with limited support for this display I think people should start adopting it in their designs so we can force more people to upgrade their browsers, so that everyone can anjoy a modern browsing experience.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Over the next few days I&#39;ll do my best to post some simple tutorials using flexbox and some of the new CSS3 tricks I&#39;ve learned over the weekend while I made my site.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In the meantime you should check out&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;http://flexboxin5.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;flexboxin5&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;it helped me figure out what I was doing and what to include in my CSS to fix the layouts. It&#39;s a great tutorial&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Don&#39;t forget to check out the new design!&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://zacblanco.github.io/&quot;&gt;zacblanco.github.io&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Zac
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 09 Mar 2015 05:29:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://zacblanco.github.io//2015/03/updated-site.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://zacblanco.github.io//2015/03/updated-site.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Internship</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;css-full-post-content js-full-post-content&quot;&gt;
Just thought it would be fun to share here. As of today I am confirmed to be working as an intern this summer with Hortonworks; a major corporate contributor to the open-source Hadoop platform.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I still have a lot to learn as a ECE/Comp. Sci student, but I&#39;m sure this internship will prepare me for the future. I know that I&#39;ll be surrounded by some of the best minds in the industry this summer and I really hope to learn as much as I can from my future colleagues.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In light of this I thought it would be fun to make a new desktop background. I took a large image of the Hortonworks logo, the image editor GIMP and a little magic to pull this together:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;separator&quot; style=&quot;clear: both; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-S1nePG9AdvQ/VPf1tYvdE3I/AAAAAAAAEBg/hMMzj7M4Uts/s1600/Hortonworks.png&quot; imageanchor=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;&quot;&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; src=&quot;http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-S1nePG9AdvQ/VPf1tYvdE3I/AAAAAAAAEBg/hMMzj7M4Uts/s1600/Hortonworks.png&quot; height=&quot;200&quot; width=&quot;320&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Feel free to copy and redistribute this too!&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Cheers to a (hopefully) fantastic opportunity.
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2015 06:23:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://zacblanco.github.io//2015/03/internship.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://zacblanco.github.io//2015/03/internship.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Projects and More Interesting Updates</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;css-full-post-content js-full-post-content&quot;&gt;
So I&#39;ve been pretty busy these last two weeks with schoolwork and other matters so I haven&#39;t had much time to update anything here.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I did want to let you know that I started working on a Java library use and to implement statistics functions that I think would be useful to analyze large datasets.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;For now I&#39;m calling the project DStat (unless someone can come up with a better name). It will hopefully become a fully fledged statistics library for performing operations on multiple types of distributions of data. As of now it only has a few functions, but feel free to take a look at that and the other projects over at my &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/zacblanco&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;GitHub page&lt;/a&gt;. I try to make progress whenever I find free time to do a little extra work. Feel free to contribute too! Everything I do I release as open source.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I eventually would like to be able to take some data you might find from your own &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/settings/takeout&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Google Data Archive&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;and within a few minutes (using DStat of course!) come up with some neat conclusions based on your own search habits or other usage statistics. Of course it might be some time before that&#39;s possible I hope that in time you will be able to find that kind of functionality with it.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2015 00:01:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://zacblanco.github.io//2015/03/projects-and-more-interesting-updates.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://zacblanco.github.io//2015/03/projects-and-more-interesting-updates.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Data....Science?</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;css-full-post-content js-full-post-content&quot;&gt;
So, I&#39;ll have to break it to you now I guess. If you couldn&#39;t already tell from the title of this blog I&#39;m really into the whole &#39;big data&#39; thing. I think data science is a really cool and interesting field that&#39;s starting to emerge. Universities are offering new courses on data science and some are even starting degree programs.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;This past semester I took a Byrne Seminar called &lt;i&gt;Data: What is it Good for? (Absolutely Something)&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;It was taught by two ECE faculty here at Rutgers. I&#39;ll link to their pages at the end.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The class really opened up my eyes to this whole whole new prospect of data and put it in this different light. We don&#39;t realize the potential that all these numbers have. They all tell part of a huge story, and the data tells different stories too! The possibilities are really almost endless.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I&#39;m excited to be in the position I am in now to see how the field evolves over the next 5-10 years and what advances we make.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I&#39;m also really interested in machine learning and the solutions it proposes to solving some problems.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Here&#39;s an interesting video I found over at &lt;a href=&quot;http://reddit.com/r/machinelearning&quot;&gt;reddit.com/r/machinelearning&lt;/a&gt; on teaching computers how to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xKt21ucdBY0&quot;&gt;automatically caption digital photographs&lt;/a&gt;. I found it really interesting.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Links to my professor&#39;s pages. I think they have some really interesting research.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ece.rutgers.edu/~asarwate/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Anand Sarwate&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rci.rutgers.edu/~wub1/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Waheed Bajwa&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2015 01:16:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://zacblanco.github.io//2015/02/datascience.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://zacblanco.github.io//2015/02/datascience.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>data</category>
        
        <category>data science</category>
        
        <category>bajwa</category>
        
        <category>science</category>
        
        <category>sarwate</category>
        
        <category>intro</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Creation</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;css-full-post-content js-full-post-content&quot;&gt;
Being the first post here I feel compelled to at least introduce myself to anyone who decides to read my blog.&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;My name is Zac Blanco. I&#39;m currently an undergraduate studying Electrical and Computer Engineering at Rutgers University. I hope to also double major with computer science, and eventually continue on to graduate school. My expected graduation date is May of 2018&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;I wanted to start a blog to share my thoughts and ideas about any of my work, projects, and other interests. Most topics here will converge on ideas in computer science theory, programming, and technology.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Enjoy!&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2015 16:57:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://zacblanco.github.io//2015/02/creation.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://zacblanco.github.io//2015/02/creation.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>about</category>
        
        <category>introduction</category>
        
        <category>first</category>
        
        <category>post</category>
        
        <category>me</category>
        
        <category>topics</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
