<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>zacblanco.github.io</title>
    <description>A simple tech blog to keepp you updated on my projects and for interesting  tips tricks and hacks.
</description>
    <link>http://zacblanco.github.io//</link>
    <atom:link href="http://zacblanco.github.io//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2015 15:45:09 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2015 15:45:09 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Neural Networks and the Backpropagation Algorithm</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The other day I had been looking up information on &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Machine_learning&quot;&gt;machine learning&lt;/a&gt;. I’m new to some of the topics in this field but I have been introduced to some before. I’ve always wanted to learn more. The idea of teaching a computer how to “learn” just seems intriguing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Specifically I had been researching &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Artificial_neural_network&quot;&gt;neural networks&lt;/a&gt;. They are useful because they can help uncover hidden patterns in a plethora of data, or be taught to perform certain tasks such as handwriting or facial recognition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had watched an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=q0pm3BrIUFo&quot;&gt;MIT Open CourseWare Lecture&lt;/a&gt; which gave a rough introduction to neural networks which I found to be quite captivating. I found it so fantastic actually that I wanted to share the basic concepts here. For the purpose of this post, I’m going to assume that we’re teaching this neural net via supervised learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, in other words, we are going to make this neural network learn by giving it a set of “correct” input and output values, which it will use to calibrate, or change its own structure to make sure that it also outputs the correct values. Now let’s dive in!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To explain briefly, neural networks are modeled after the same neurons that exist in our brain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/b/b5/Neuron.svg/500px-Neuron.svg.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of Neuron&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For our purpose we focus on only a few of the main features of a neuron which are critical to our model for a neural network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main parts of the neuron we want to focus on are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dendrites&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Axon&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Axon Terminals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The dendrites&lt;/strong&gt; are small tree-like structures that are stimulated when enough neurotransmitters are dumped into the synapse between a neuron and the end of the dendrite. Some of these dendrites might be easier to stimulate than other based on various factors&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The axon&lt;/strong&gt; is the lengthy part of the neuron which simply propagates a “spike” of energy to the axon terminals, which originates from the dendrites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The axon terminals&lt;/strong&gt; dump neurotransmitters into the synapse to help stimulate the dendrites of the next neuron.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there are enough neurotransmitters dumped into the synapse, It will stimulate the next neuron’s dendrites, sending a spike of “excitement” or “energy” to the next neuron, and so forth. At each end of the axom terminals there is another neuron’s dendrites separated by a space called the &lt;strong&gt;synapse&lt;/strong&gt;. If a neuron is stimulated, it will dump neurotransmitters into the synapse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a gross simplification of a neuron, but for the model of a neural network and the backpropagation algorithm, we don’t need to understand more than this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;modeling-the-neuron&quot;&gt;Modeling the Neuron&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/neural-nets/net-model.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Image of Model&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, notice the inputs. Each input from &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;x_1&lt;/script&gt; to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;x_n&lt;/script&gt; is given as an input to the neuron. Each of the inputs is multiplied by a weight &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;w&lt;/script&gt; corresponding to an input before being summed into the function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The neuron also has a bias, labeled  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;b&lt;/script&gt; in the diagram, which I like to call &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;w_0&lt;/script&gt;. We can think of this bias as a given input to each neuron that always has a value of -1. The weight of the bias input &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;w_0&lt;/script&gt; can be adjusted accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think of this part as the neurotransmitters being the inputs multiplied by the weights which stimulate the dendrites of the neuron.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From here we can represent the total stimulus as the sum of each input multiplied by a corresponding weight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;-w_0 + \sum_{i=1}^{n}x_iw_i&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The value of this will be then be passed onto the activation, or &lt;em&gt;threshold&lt;/em&gt; function. The threshold function might be best viewed as a single-step function, where say once the input &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\alpha&lt;/script&gt; reaches a certain value, it will output a certain value. We’re going to keep this to ones and zeros.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/neural-nets/threshold-med.png&quot; alt=&quot;Threshold Example&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, once the threshold is activated or not, we will get an output from this neuron. Once we run this neural network through for the first time, we are going to need to find out how good (or bad) the neural network did at predicting our answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember how I said that the neural network is given a set of “correct” inputs and outputs to learn from? Well here’s where that comes into play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say that our output of the neural net is &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;y&lt;/script&gt; and our desired or &lt;em&gt;correct&lt;/em&gt; output is going to be assigned to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;d&lt;/script&gt;. We are going to need a function to test our performance of the neural network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s call this function &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;P&lt;/script&gt;. Also, for simplicity’s sake, and because this is &lt;em&gt;mathematically convenient&lt;/em&gt; we’re going to make the performance function the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;P(d, y) = -\frac{1}{2}(d-y)^2&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(&lt;em&gt;You’ll see what I mean by mathematically convenient later&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;adjusting-the-model&quot;&gt;Adjusting the Model&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now we’ve got this model. We have a function to test whether our output is close to what we want it to be. We have a way to add our inputs together. What comes next?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, we need to have some way of adjusting the neuron to make sure we get closer to our desired output. But how do we know what to adjust? and by how much?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re going to use a method called &lt;strong&gt;gradient descent&lt;/strong&gt; (or &lt;em&gt;ascent&lt;/em&gt; depending on direction). We’re going to use some math here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we know that our desired outputs &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;d&lt;/script&gt; can be given by &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\overline{d} = g(\overline{x})&lt;/script&gt;; where &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\overline{d}&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\overline{x}&lt;/script&gt; are our vectors of inputs and desired outputs that our neural network is going to learn from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem is that we don’t know what function &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;g&lt;/script&gt; is, which is why we’re using the neural network to represent it. With the neural networks, we can represent our inputs and outputs by a multivaraite function &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;f&lt;/script&gt;. This function can be represented by &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\overline{y} = f(\overline{x}, \overline{w})&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given these functions, we can see our performance function is now&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;P(d, f(\overline{x}, \overline{w})) = -\frac{1}{2}(d-f(\overline{x}, \overline{w}))^2&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Random junk&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\sum_{i=0}^{N} = 1&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/4/46/Colored_neural_network.svg/300px-Colored_neural_network.svg.png&quot; alt=&quot;Model of Neural Net&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2015 15:45:08 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://zacblanco.github.io//nerual-networks-and-backpropagation.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://zacblanco.github.io//nerual-networks-and-backpropagation.html</guid>
        
        <category>neural networks</category>
        
        <category>machine learning</category>
        
        <category>AI</category>
        
        <category>artificial intelligence</category>
        
        <category>MIT</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hosting your Jekyll site with GitHub Pages</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As a continuation to the series of the last few posts I will be explaining how to host your jekyll site for &lt;strong&gt;free&lt;/strong&gt; using &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;. GitHub provides completely free website hosting using your own GitHub account. For more information I suggest reading up on &lt;a href=&quot;https://pages.github.com/&quot;&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First off, you’re going to need to &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/join&quot;&gt;create an account on GitHub&lt;/a&gt; if you haven’t already. GitHub is a fantastic site that can host private and public git repositories for your personal projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a list of a few advantages to using GitHub Pages:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Completely Free&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A site for every project&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use your own domain name&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Completely integrated with Git&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course some disadvantages:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;No server side scripting&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;No control over how the site is served&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;No secure connections with &lt;code&gt;https&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now this really isn’t a complete list, but these are some of the things I thought would stand out to most people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now for the fun part! Let’s get started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;create-a-repository-for-your-site&quot;&gt;Create a Repository for Your Site&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First make sure that you’re logged in to GitHub. Then, head over to your GitHub profile located at &lt;code&gt;https://github.com/username&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the top of the screen click the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;+&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; button at the top of the page and create a new repository. You &lt;strong&gt;MUST&lt;/strong&gt; name the repository in the following way: &lt;code&gt;username.github.io&lt;/code&gt;. Your site will not be created if it is not named correctly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we’ve got your site’s repository set up we can finally add your Jekyll files to that repository.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let’s head back to the desktop and open a new terminal window. Using the terminal navigate to the desired folder where you would like your project to be contained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, assuming you’ve got git installed we’re going to use the following command:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;    ~ $ git clone https://github.com/username/username.github.io
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now check using &lt;code&gt;ls&lt;/code&gt; or by opening up a new finder window, navigate to the same folder you just had by using the terminal and you should find a new folder by the name of &lt;code&gt;username.github.io&lt;/code&gt;. Open up this folder. This is the place where we will copy your Jekyll files to be pushed to GitHub’s servers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now assuming you’ve already built a Jekyll site, copy the files from your site into this folder. Go back to your terminal window and &lt;code&gt;cd&lt;/code&gt; into &lt;code&gt;username.github.io&lt;/code&gt; folder. Then type the following commands&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;    ~ $ git add --all
    ~ $ git commit -m &quot;Init Commit&quot;
    ~ $ git push -u origin master
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve done that, congratulations! You’ve made your first GitHub pages site! Open up a web browser and head over to &lt;code&gt;http://username.github.io&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The site should be live within a few minutes. New changes after this should be live within seconds of pushing to the server.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;an-alternative-method&quot;&gt;An Alternative Method&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you do not have git installed on your computer, or you are unfamiliar with the command line, &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; you’re running Microsoft Windows or Mac OS X, there’s another method you can use to get your site running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Download &lt;a href=&quot;https://windows.github.com/&quot;&gt;GitHub for Windows&lt;/a&gt; if you’re running Windows, or &lt;a href=&quot;https://mac.github.com/&quot;&gt;GitHub for Mac&lt;/a&gt; if you’re running OS X. Once you install GitHub’s software, login to the git client. You should see a list of your repositories within the software. Clone the repository that we just created on GitHub. There should be a menu to do this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you open a file browser, look for a folder in the location &lt;code&gt;~/username/documents/GitHub/username.github.io&lt;/code&gt;. This is the location where your repository is located. You can copy your files from the Jekyll site into that folder. Once you’ve done that, head over to the GitHub software and name your commit, add a message if you’d like. Then &lt;code&gt;commit&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;sync&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve synced your repository, you can open a web browser and navigate to &lt;code&gt;http://username.github.io&lt;/code&gt; where your site should be live in a matter of seconds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your site is not appearing, then you may have named your repository wrong, or you might have to wait a few minutes for the servers to create your site. Wait at least 10 minutes to see if your site is up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re having trouble refer to the github pages documentation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another great thing about GitHub pages is that on top of having a site for yourself, you are allowed a site for each project you have located at &lt;code&gt;http://username.github.io/project-name&lt;/code&gt;. This is a great way to host many pages and to allow people to access and learn more about your open source project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully this brief guide was enough for you to get your site set up on GitHub Pages. Good luck!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 18 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://zacblanco.github.io//hosting-with-github-pages.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://zacblanco.github.io//hosting-with-github-pages.html</guid>
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
        <category>site</category>
        
        <category>poole</category>
        
        <category>web</category>
        
        <category>hosting</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Adding Flavor to Jekyll</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;So you’ve got your Jekyll site running, you can write some posts, but it still doesn’t feel like your own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where Jekyll can be awesome, but also slightly confusing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the core, Jekyll takes a markdown file and uses it’s templating system called &lt;strong&gt;liquid&lt;/strong&gt; to help insert html and structure pages, and all of this is then converted into static html files that can be served on a web server.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the rest of this post I’m going to assume that you at least know how to build your site with Jekyll and serve it locally to your web browser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;liquid&quot;&gt;Liquid&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to breeze over liquid right now, but I suggest that you take a look at &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/docs/templates/&quot;&gt;the liquid templating features in Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be brief, &lt;strong&gt;liquid&lt;/strong&gt; allows us to pull sitewide variables and html code and place them right into our pages with ease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In your posts and any pages on  your Jekyll site by calling sitewide variables to insert values into your pages. In one of your posts, try adding the following.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;##### [Homepage]({{ site.url  }})
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The previous code should produce a link that directs you to your blog’s homepage. See below for it in action!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;h5 id=&quot;homepagehttpzacblancogithubio&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://zacblanco.github.io&quot;&gt;Homepage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;changing-the-style-of-your-site&quot;&gt;Changing the Style of Your Site&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll has a whole host of themes that can change the look of your site. This includes downloading and installing prebuilt themes, or diving straight in to the &lt;code&gt;sass&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;css&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;_layouts&lt;/code&gt; foldera of the site to change how it looks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sass-and-css&quot;&gt;sass and CSS&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, this sass is not the same thing that you gave to your mother when you were a teenager. Sass is a version of css that can be run through a compiler  to compile css. If you’d like to learn more about sass, &lt;a href=&quot;http://sass-lang.com/&quot;&gt;click here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take a look inside the &lt;code&gt;css&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;_sass&lt;/code&gt; folder within the directory of your jekyll site. Although these files are not &lt;code&gt;.css&lt;/code&gt; files, you can still write normal css, and if you know sass, you can write sass too. The files that you modify will change the corresponding sitewide visuals based on those files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;layouts&quot;&gt;_Layouts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;_layouts&lt;/code&gt; folder is where you can write html templates for certain types of pages on your site. There should currently be at least one layout with the name &lt;code&gt;default&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;page&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;post&lt;/code&gt;. These names are the same names you will specify in the &lt;code&gt;yaml&lt;/code&gt; at the beginning of a post, or page that you write. An example of the &lt;code&gt;yaml&lt;/code&gt; header for this page is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;    ---
    layout: post
    title: Adding Flavor to Jekyll
    tags: [jekyll, poole, site, css, web]
    ---
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can see that the layout type for this post is &lt;code&gt;post&lt;/code&gt; which tells Jekyll to use the &lt;code&gt;post.html&lt;/code&gt; layout to format and style this page. You can also edit these files to change the look of your site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;poole&quot;&gt;Poole&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally on this site I use a theme called &lt;a href=&quot;http://getpoole.com/&quot;&gt;Poole&lt;/a&gt;. If you would like to use this theme for your own site you can download and replace all of the &lt;code&gt;layout&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;css&lt;/code&gt; files with the ones from Poole. It’s a very simple and easy to use theme. Follow the documentation for the installation procedure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;wrapping-up&quot;&gt;Wrapping Up&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully from here you can better understand how Jekyll generates the site pages on your site. A bit of research and some work can make your site unique! You can also add new features and pages too by using the layouts and css files too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope now that you have enough knowledge about the structure of a Jekyll site to be able to customize it to your liking.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 17 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://zacblanco.github.io//adding-flavor-to-jekyll.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://zacblanco.github.io//adding-flavor-to-jekyll.html</guid>
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
        <category>poole</category>
        
        <category>site</category>
        
        <category>css</category>
        
        <category>web</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Building a Site with Jekyll</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;So I when I first started trying to make a blog I didn’t realize how difficult it would actually be to find something that worked. No other free platform contained the features that I wanted. And as a college student we should know that, free = good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; is no perfect solution, but it does provide a host of features and is much more open than any other option I could find, which is why I opted to switch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a quick intro, Jekyll straight out of the box really isn’t anything special. Basically it takes some text that you write up for your posts and converts them into some static html files that can be served to a user.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Posts are written in &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Markdown&quot;&gt;Markdown&lt;/a&gt; which is a really handy markup language. Great for writing posts, but it does have a bit of a learning curve and takes some time to get used to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another great thing about using Jekyll is that there’s quite a bit of resources, and its open source! It’s very flexible, you can use plugins, create new themes, and add commenting features. This list just goes on!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creating a site from scratch with Jekyll is definitely not for the faint-hearted. If you’re willing to put the time and effort in you can come out with a blog customized to your very liking including only the features you would like. It’s a very hands-on get-dirty-with-the-code project, but it’s a lot of fun and you might learn a few things along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of this post I’ll be showing you how exactly to install and run Jekyll to &lt;em&gt;quickly&lt;/em&gt; create your own static website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;prerequisites&quot;&gt;Prerequisites&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;please-download-ruby-first-then-rubygems&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please download ruby first, then RubyGems&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re going to need &lt;strong&gt;ruby&lt;/strong&gt; installed on your machine. If you dont have ruby installed &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ruby-lang.org/en/downloads/&quot;&gt;you can get it here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re also going to have to install &lt;a href=&quot;https://rubygems.org/pages/download&quot;&gt;RubyGems&lt;/a&gt;. It’s package manager for ruby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I’m going to assume you know how to install these or already have them on your system. Follow the documentation provided online or do a quick google search if you’re having any trouble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve got them both installed, open up a command terminal and try this command&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;~ user$ ruby --version
~ user$ gem --version
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If everything works correctly you should get some type of outputs similar to this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;ruby 2.0.0p481 (2014-05-08 revision 45883) [universal.x86_64-darwin14]
2.0.14
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Great! now we have the two essentials installed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;getting-jekyll&quot;&gt;Getting Jekyll&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a valid internet connection and a command terminal, use the following commands to install Jekyll on your machine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;~ user$ sudo gem install jekyll
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check now that you have the latest version of Jekyll installed by using&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;~ user$ jekyll --version
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;creating-your-first-site&quot;&gt;Creating your first site&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s where things start getting fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using your terminal, navigate to the chosen directory on your filesystem where you would like to keep your code, site, and any other files &lt;em&gt;(Preferably a location where you might keep some repositories)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assuming you’ve already navigated there perform the following&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;~/location/ user$ jekyll new &amp;lt;site-name&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or if you’d like to have jekyll generate the files in the folder you’re currently located in&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;~/site-name/ user$ jekyll new .
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now if you use ls command or view that directory you just created inside a file manager you should see something similar to the following&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;_config.yml	_layouts    _sass	css		index.html
_includes	_posts		about.md	feed.xml
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;configyml&quot;&gt;_config.yml&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This file is where we store some sitewide variables, like author name, baseurl, twitter and GitHub handles, etc. Edit the variables in here as you like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;posts&quot;&gt;_posts&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where you’re going to write posts in the Markdown syntax. I suggest an editor than can support previews of Markdown. Personally I use &lt;a href=&quot;http://brackets.io&quot;&gt;Adobe Brackets&lt;/a&gt; with the Markdown plugin to preview. More on all of this later&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;aboutmd&quot;&gt;about.md&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a markdown file you can edit to change the “About” page on your site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;includes-layouts-sass-css&quot;&gt;_includes, _layouts, _sass, css&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are all other places where you can change configurations and views of your site. The layout and css can all be found under these places. We’re not really going to edit those right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;making-your-first-post&quot;&gt;Making your first post&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lets navigate to our folder and create a new post. Create a new file and name is something following the scheme: &lt;code&gt;YYYY-MM-DD-your-title.md&lt;/code&gt;. Open this new file in a text editor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inside we’re going to put:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;---
layout: post
title: Hello World!
---

# Howdy there partner
Congratulations! You&#39;ve made it to[site](site.url)

We&#39;re ust getting started here.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now save your document and return to the terminal that has navigated inside of your site’s directory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;building-the-site&quot;&gt;Building the Site&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Run the following command&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;~/location/ user$ jekyll build
~/location/ user$ jekyll serve
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leave the terminal open. Open up a new tab in your browser of choice and navigate to &lt;code&gt;http://localhost:4000&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should see a home page with a link to Jekyll’s default page for new sites, and your own post we just wrote!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Click on the post to make sure it works there. If it does, congratulations! you’ve made your first blog post using Jekyll&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s tons more you can do with themes, pages, and other sweet customizations for your shiny new blog, but I’ll go into those at a later date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now, play around with Jekyll and get a feel for the software. It’s something interesting that I’ve never encountered before and is definitely worth a try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy blogging!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://zacblanco.github.io//starting-with-jekyll.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://zacblanco.github.io//starting-with-jekyll.html</guid>
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
        <category>hyde</category>
        
        <category>site</category>
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
        <category>markdown</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Blog transfer</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;css-full-post-content js-full-post-content&quot;&gt;
Since I&#39;m pretty new to blogging I haven&#39;t found the platform yet that I like best. I decided blogger was a little too plain and wordpress had some better layouts but didn&#39;t give me enough control, so I&#39;ve decided to move to jekyll hosting using github pages.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I won&#39;t be posting here any longer. Please direct all traffic to &lt;a href=&quot;http://zacblanco.github.io/&quot;&gt;zacblanco.github.io&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;EDIT:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I just want to add my previous post about an updated site-- well. Now that I&#39;m using Jekyll I won&#39;t be able to keep that as the landing page. You can still find it and view-source &lt;a href=&quot;http://zacblanco.github.io/s-old/index.html&quot;&gt;zacblanco.github.io/s-old/index.html&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 09 Mar 2015 17:50:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://zacblanco.github.io//2015/03/blog-transfer.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://zacblanco.github.io//2015/03/blog-transfer.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Updated Site</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;css-full-post-content js-full-post-content&quot;&gt;
So I just wanted to let you guys know that I&#39;ve updated my GitHub pages site. Because I like learning and building things form scratch to learn how everything is put together I built my site from the ground up and learned a few things along the way.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I was inspired to do this redesign after I came across flexbox. A CSS display property that I had not previously known of. It makes a lot of resizing and overall site layout much easier. I was inspired to rebuild my site using this.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The great thing is that flexbox is easy. It just works. and It&#39;s trivial to center things in your screen and resize the browser causing them to flow onto other line. It really is a great tool. The one caveat is that it doesn&#39;t have great browser support.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I&#39;ve currently tested on the most updated versions of the major browsers (IE, Chrome, Firefox, Safari) and so far Chrome and Firefox render the page properly. Unfortunately however, Safari definitely does not render the page properly. Most older browsers don&#39;t Although I&#39;m not too worried about this. Even with improper display the page is still navigable. IE11 surprisingly does. Even with limited support for this display I think people should start adopting it in their designs so we can force more people to upgrade their browsers, so that everyone can anjoy a modern browsing experience.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Over the next few days I&#39;ll do my best to post some simple tutorials using flexbox and some of the new CSS3 tricks I&#39;ve learned over the weekend while I made my site.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In the meantime you should check out&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;http://flexboxin5.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;flexboxin5&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;it helped me figure out what I was doing and what to include in my CSS to fix the layouts. It&#39;s a great tutorial&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Don&#39;t forget to check out the new design!&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://zacblanco.github.io/&quot;&gt;zacblanco.github.io&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Zac
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 09 Mar 2015 05:29:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://zacblanco.github.io//2015/03/updated-site.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://zacblanco.github.io//2015/03/updated-site.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Internship</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;css-full-post-content js-full-post-content&quot;&gt;
Just thought it would be fun to share here. As of today I am confirmed to be working as an intern this summer with Hortonworks; a major corporate contributor to the open-source Hadoop platform.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I still have a lot to learn as a ECE/Comp. Sci student, but I&#39;m sure this internship will prepare me for the future. I know that I&#39;ll be surrounded by some of the best minds in the industry this summer and I really hope to learn as much as I can from my future colleagues.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In light of this I thought it would be fun to make a new desktop background. I took a large image of the Hortonworks logo, the image editor GIMP and a little magic to pull this together:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;separator&quot; style=&quot;clear: both; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-S1nePG9AdvQ/VPf1tYvdE3I/AAAAAAAAEBg/hMMzj7M4Uts/s1600/Hortonworks.png&quot; imageanchor=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;&quot;&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; src=&quot;http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-S1nePG9AdvQ/VPf1tYvdE3I/AAAAAAAAEBg/hMMzj7M4Uts/s1600/Hortonworks.png&quot; height=&quot;200&quot; width=&quot;320&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Feel free to copy and redistribute this too!&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Cheers to a (hopefully) fantastic opportunity.
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2015 06:23:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://zacblanco.github.io//2015/03/internship.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://zacblanco.github.io//2015/03/internship.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Projects and More Interesting Updates</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;css-full-post-content js-full-post-content&quot;&gt;
So I&#39;ve been pretty busy these last two weeks with schoolwork and other matters so I haven&#39;t had much time to update anything here.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I did want to let you know that I started working on a Java library use and to implement statistics functions that I think would be useful to analyze large datasets.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;For now I&#39;m calling the project DStat (unless someone can come up with a better name). It will hopefully become a fully fledged statistics library for performing operations on multiple types of distributions of data. As of now it only has a few functions, but feel free to take a look at that and the other projects over at my &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/zacblanco&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;GitHub page&lt;/a&gt;. I try to make progress whenever I find free time to do a little extra work. Feel free to contribute too! Everything I do I release as open source.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I eventually would like to be able to take some data you might find from your own &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/settings/takeout&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Google Data Archive&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;and within a few minutes (using DStat of course!) come up with some neat conclusions based on your own search habits or other usage statistics. Of course it might be some time before that&#39;s possible I hope that in time you will be able to find that kind of functionality with it.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2015 00:01:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://zacblanco.github.io//2015/03/projects-and-more-interesting-updates.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://zacblanco.github.io//2015/03/projects-and-more-interesting-updates.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Data....Science?</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;css-full-post-content js-full-post-content&quot;&gt;
So, I&#39;ll have to break it to you now I guess. If you couldn&#39;t already tell from the title of this blog I&#39;m really into the whole &#39;big data&#39; thing. I think data science is a really cool and interesting field that&#39;s starting to emerge. Universities are offering new courses on data science and some are even starting degree programs.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;This past semester I took a Byrne Seminar called &lt;i&gt;Data: What is it Good for? (Absolutely Something)&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;It was taught by two ECE faculty here at Rutgers. I&#39;ll link to their pages at the end.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The class really opened up my eyes to this whole whole new prospect of data and put it in this different light. We don&#39;t realize the potential that all these numbers have. They all tell part of a huge story, and the data tells different stories too! The possibilities are really almost endless.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I&#39;m excited to be in the position I am in now to see how the field evolves over the next 5-10 years and what advances we make.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I&#39;m also really interested in machine learning and the solutions it proposes to solving some problems.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Here&#39;s an interesting video I found over at &lt;a href=&quot;http://reddit.com/r/machinelearning&quot;&gt;reddit.com/r/machinelearning&lt;/a&gt; on teaching computers how to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xKt21ucdBY0&quot;&gt;automatically caption digital photographs&lt;/a&gt;. I found it really interesting.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Links to my professor&#39;s pages. I think they have some really interesting research.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ece.rutgers.edu/~asarwate/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Anand Sarwate&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rci.rutgers.edu/~wub1/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Waheed Bajwa&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2015 01:16:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://zacblanco.github.io//2015/02/datascience.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://zacblanco.github.io//2015/02/datascience.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>data</category>
        
        <category>data science</category>
        
        <category>bajwa</category>
        
        <category>science</category>
        
        <category>sarwate</category>
        
        <category>intro</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Creation</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;css-full-post-content js-full-post-content&quot;&gt;
Being the first post here I feel compelled to at least introduce myself to anyone who decides to read my blog.&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;My name is Zac Blanco. I&#39;m currently an undergraduate studying Electrical and Computer Engineering at Rutgers University. I hope to also double major with computer science, and eventually continue on to graduate school. My expected graduation date is May of 2018&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;I wanted to start a blog to share my thoughts and ideas about any of my work, projects, and other interests. Most topics here will converge on ideas in computer science theory, programming, and technology.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Enjoy!&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2015 16:57:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://zacblanco.github.io//2015/02/creation.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://zacblanco.github.io//2015/02/creation.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>about</category>
        
        <category>introduction</category>
        
        <category>first</category>
        
        <category>post</category>
        
        <category>me</category>
        
        <category>topics</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
