<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>zacblanco.github.io</title>
    <description>A personal site to outline my professional experience, as well as showcase my small part-time projects. I enjoy writing posts from time to time whenever I learn something new or feel like sharing things with the world.
</description>
    <link>http://zacblanco.github.io//</link>
    <atom:link href="http://zacblanco.github.io//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 28 Sep 2015 10:59:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 28 Sep 2015 10:59:00 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>My Summer Experience at Hortonworks</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;So this past summer I worked for a company called &lt;a href=&quot;http://hortonworks.com&quot;&gt;Hortonworks&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../../assets/images/hortonworks-review/hortonworks-logo-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Hortonworks Logo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole experience this summer was much more than I had ever expected to come from this internship. It really opened my eyes (and a few doors!) for my career and other years to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This summer I interned for a second time with the Hortonworks security team where I helped to develop enterprise-grade security for the Hadoop ecosystem with &lt;a href=&quot;http://knox.apache.org&quot;&gt;Apache Knox&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://knox.apache.org&quot;&gt;Apache Knox&lt;/a&gt; is a gateway server (also called a proxy) that helps to provide perimeter security for hadoop services. You can access many Hadoop services over &lt;code&gt;HTTP&lt;/code&gt;, but instead of accessing them on a variety of different servers and ports, Knox brings all the services together and allows for a single point of access to all of the services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This allows a single point for security authentication, authorization, and auditing to occur as well. This makes aggregating usage and logon data very easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Knox provides many other features as well. I suggest reading up on it over at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://knox.apache.org&quot;&gt;project page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other security project that is a part of the Hadoop ecosystem is called &lt;a href=&quot;http://ranger.apache.org&quot;&gt;Apache Ranger&lt;/a&gt;. It helps govern access to Hadoop services through poly management. I did not directly work on this project but I felt it should at least get a shout out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found the experience that I gained over this summer invaluable as I learned not only about becoming a great software engineer, but I also developed professional skills as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My mentor was probably my biggest motivation in this entire job. He coached me through many, many situations and was always willing to lend a helping hand in my work (so long as he wasn’t busy!). Not to mention he had the patience of a saint. With his help I was able to learn and reflect on my experiences. He questioned and challenged me to do the best work I could - while always providing helpful criticism and guidance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hortonworks as a company had a better culture than I could have imagined. Everyone that worked here was very intelligent and knowledge in their respective areas. It really seems that Hortonworks wants to employ the best of the best, the cream of the crop. And it really shows in the software and product that they provide to their customers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone at this company is passionate about what they do - which also goes a long way in seeing the work that they produce. I am very excited to see where this company is heading in the near future. I know it will be a good place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I commend Hortonworks and our &lt;a href=&quot;http://interns.hortonworks.com&quot;&gt;Hortonworks Internship Program&lt;/a&gt; coordinator Christina for putting together the intern program and providing everyone this summer with a chance to gain valuable experience in a small, but very quickly growing, company. We were able to get a taste of Silicon Valley and what life like is there. As well as participate in many company events and make us feel like we were part of the team too!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole experience was really enjoyable. I especially liked that we had the chance to meet with many VP’s, founders, and other high-profile employees. It really made us feel like we mattered to them. Especially the fact that those employees helped judge our project presentations at the end!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall my experience this summer was spectacular and I really can’t wait to see where Hadoop goes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../../assets/images/hortonworks-review/hadoop-logo-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Hadoop Logo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 12 Sep 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://zacblanco.github.io//blog/professional/my-experience-at-hortonworks</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://zacblanco.github.io//blog/professional/my-experience-at-hortonworks</guid>
        
        <category>hortonworks</category>
        
        <category>professional</category>
        
        <category>experience</category>
        
        <category>rutgers</category>
        
        <category>internship</category>
        
        <category>software</category>
        
        <category>engineering</category>
        
        <category>software engineer</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A (Somewhat) Comprehensive Guide to Physics 227 at Rutgers University</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;So here we are again - another semester of introductory physics at Rutgers University, New Brunswick. This is the Fall 2015 semester. This will be a kind-of continuation from the Physics IB guide from the previous spring 2015 semester.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aim of this is post/page to provide a (somewhat) comprehensive guide to this class by periodically updating it throughout the semester. My plan is to make notes during lecture as well as provide practice problems and explanations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without furthur ado - Let’s dive in!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;september-3rd-2015&quot;&gt;September 3rd, 2015&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost everything in the universe can be described by just 4 (!) equations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;electric-charge&quot;&gt;Electric Charge&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Electric Charge&lt;/em&gt; is a physical quantity that characterizes how charged object participate in electrostatic interactions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;electric-charge-properties&quot;&gt;Electric Charge Properties&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is a scalar value&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is quantizes - meaning that a charge must be in integer multiples of the fundamental value of charge&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This fundamental amount is the charge of an electron.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;e = 1.6 \cdot 10^{-19} Coulombs&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The net charge of any isolated system is &lt;em&gt;conserved&lt;/em&gt;. i.e the net charge of the universe is zero&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;coulombs-law&quot;&gt;Coulomb’s Law&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coulomb’s law describes the &lt;em&gt;forces&lt;/em&gt; that charged particles exert on each other due to…well…simply their charge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The equation for Coulomb’s law is the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;F_{12} = k\frac{\left|q_1q_2\right|}{r^2}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let’s quickly describe each quantity&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;F_{12}&lt;/script&gt; is the force that each particle exerts on one another. This means that &lt;em&gt;both particles experience the same force&lt;/em&gt;!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;k&lt;/script&gt; is a constant value expressed in this function. It’s value is equal to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{1}{4\pi\epsilon_0}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;q_1&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;q_2&lt;/script&gt; are the charges of each particle measured in  &lt;em&gt;Coulomb’s&lt;/em&gt; or the symbol &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;C&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;r&lt;/script&gt; is the distance between the two charges.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;k = \frac{1}{4\pi\epsilon_0} = 9*10^9 \frac{Nm^2}{C^2}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\epsilon_0 = 9 * 10^{-12} \frac{C^2}{Nm^2}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-superposition-principle&quot;&gt;The Superposition Principle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This principle states that the &lt;em&gt;interaction between any two charges is unaffected by any other charges present&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This principle also tells us that the equations are &lt;em&gt;linear&lt;/em&gt;. The solutions of multiple equations can be added together to form other solutions (as in the presence of multiple charges).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;electric-dipole&quot;&gt;Electric Dipole&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An &lt;em&gt;electric dipole&lt;/em&gt; is formed by two charges &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;+q&lt;/script&gt; and  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;-q&lt;/script&gt; at the distance &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;d&lt;/script&gt; apart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that wraps up section one! I hope to keep this as up to date as possible.
If you would like to contribute to this guide please submit a pull request on GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;september-6th-2015&quot;&gt;September 6th 2015&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lecture-2---electric-field-and-electric-field-lines&quot;&gt;Lecture 2 - Electric Field and Electric Field Lines.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One great analogy for electrostatic fields is gravity. Think about it&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gravity is a force we feel due to mass. All around a massive object, the force due to gravity than another object would feel is always directed at the center of mass of the larger object no matter the position around the massive object.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now think about a negatively charged object with no mass (and every other object is a positively charged object). Every positive object would undergo a force directed at the very center of the negatively charged object (so long as it is a point charge). It wouldn’t matter the location of the positive test charges. The force is always pointing towards the same point on the negatively charged object.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;electric-field&quot;&gt;Electric Field&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Units are in &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{N}{C}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A force due to an electric field can be defined as &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\vec{F} = q\vec{E}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Another form: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\vec{E} = k\frac{q}{r^2}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s very useful to know that due to the superposition principle (mentioned above) We can add vectors of electric fields to find the &lt;em&gt;net electric field&lt;/em&gt; due to multiple charges, simply by adding the fields due do different charges at a single point. To add fields from different charges together, you must be using the &lt;em&gt;same test-point for each field&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;electric-field-lines&quot;&gt;Electric Field Lines&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The direction of the electric field vector is tangential to the field line (curve)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The intensity of the electric field at a given point is proportional to the local density of the field lines.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another way of stating it, is that at every point on a field line, the force experienced by a test charge is in a direction that is tangential to the field line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More things to note:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When drawing electric field lines, the lines should always point away from a positive charge, and either terminate at a negative charge, or at infinity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A weaker field will have less lines (less dense)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A stronger field will have more lines (more dense)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For a point charge: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;E(r) \propto \frac{1}{r^2}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The density of the lines is &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\propto \frac{1}{r^2}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The area of a sphere centered at the charge is &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\propto r^2&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;electric-polarization&quot;&gt;Electric Polarization&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Redistribution of charges within a neutral object by an external electric field. As a result, a neutral object acquires a dipole moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We call materials that have induced or built-in dipoles, &lt;strong&gt;dialectrics&lt;/strong&gt;. For example &lt;strong&gt;water&lt;/strong&gt;. Dialectrics are usually insulators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we apply an electric field to any of these dialectrics, they will polarize themselves. As is one side of the object will become more positive, and one more negative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, we have conductors that can polarize themselves because their electrons act as a “sea”. The electrons flow freely inside the metal. So if you apply and electric field, the electrons will move in the directon of the electric field, leaving some parts more positively/negatively charged than others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;september-10th-2015&quot;&gt;September 10th 2015&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lecture-3-electric-field-flux-and-gauss-law&quot;&gt;Lecture 3 Electric Field Flux and Gauss’ Law&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quick review question:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Imagine there is a negative charge, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;-Q&lt;/script&gt;, in an electric field. It is released from rest. What direction will the particle’s acceleration be?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The particle will travel &lt;em&gt;opposite&lt;/em&gt; the direction of the electric field. Positive charges will flow with the field, negative flow in the opposite direction.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;electric-flux&quot;&gt;Electric Flux&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, imagine water flowing through a pipe. How would you find the flow rate? Most people will probably want to use an equation similar to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\Delta{V} = A \cdot v \cdot 1s&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now what happens if we don’t take a perfect cross section of the pipe though? How can we calculate the flow rate through this new cut? (Imagine the cut being at an angle to the edge of the pipe rather than perpendicular). Turns out we can still find the flow rate even though the cut is different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All we have to do is simply take a dot product (or multiple through by &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;cos(\phi)&lt;/script&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So the flow rate for a different (non-perpendicular cut) is &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\Delta{V} =  \vec{A} \cdot \vec{v} \cdot 1s&lt;/script&gt; or &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\Delta{V} = Av cos(\phi)&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Equation for flux&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\Phi_a = \vec{a}(\vec{r}) \cdot d\vec{A} = a(r)A \cdot cos\phi&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Units of flux: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{Nm^2}{C}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Another Form: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\Phi_E = \vec{E} \cdot \vec{A} = \int\vec{E}(\vec{R}) \cdot d\vec{A}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;point-charge-at-the-center-of-a-spherical-object&quot;&gt;Point Charge at the Center of a Spherical Object&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;At each point of a surface &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\vec{E} * d\vec{A}&lt;/script&gt; where &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;( cos\phi=1 )&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simplified, this means that the flux for a spehere is equal to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{1}{4\pi\epsilon_0}\frac{q}{r^2}4\pi r^2&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This expression is equal to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{q}{\epsilon_0}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;So what if we pose the question: What would be the flux of the gravitational field of Earth, through Earth’s surface?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Flux of Graviatational Field &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;= -4\pi G M&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For fields that have &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{1}{r^2}&lt;/script&gt; dependence, it is true that any field lines entering an object’s surface must also exit. This means that the flix for any surface not contianing any charge, the flux is zero.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This also means &lt;em&gt;any surface deformations do not have an effect on the flux of the object&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Put simply this means that for any and all objects, the flux is dependent only upon the sum of the charge within the object,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the lecture notes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;For any closed surface, the flux of the electrostatic field would be proportional to the net charge inside the surface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gauss’ Law is also valid in electrodynamic, not just electrostatics because it is valid for &lt;strong&gt;any&lt;/strong&gt; point inside of an object.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gauss’ Law: First of Maxwell’s Equations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;applications-of-gauss-law&quot;&gt;Applications of Gauss’ Law&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gauss’ Law in its integral form (one scalar equation) is not sufficient for finding three components of a vector field, &lt;strong&gt;E&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;However, Gauss’ Law is very useful whenever it is possible to reduce a 3D (vector) problem to a 1D (scalar) problem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Useful symmetries:
- Sphereical
Cylindrical + translational
- Plane&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;an example of &lt;em&gt;insufficient&lt;/em&gt; symmetry could be an electric dipole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;spherical-symmetry&quot;&gt;Spherical Symmetry&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ex: The electric field of a uniformly charged ball. Radius &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;R&lt;/script&gt;, Total charge &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;Q&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gaussian surface: a sphere centered at the origin O. It’s radius &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;r&lt;/script&gt; can be smaller or larger than &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;R&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../../assets/images/physics-227/spherical-symmetry-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Slide with Spherical Symmetry&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;september-14th-2015&quot;&gt;September 14th 2015&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lecture-4---conductors-in-electrostatics&quot;&gt;Lecture 4 - Conductors in Electrostatics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The general problem of electrostatics is that given object carry many different charges - and we want to find out the electric field&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reminder: Gauss’ Law&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\int \vec{E}(\vec{r}) \cdot d\vec{A} = \frac{Q_{net}}{\epsilon_0}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically the law tells us that the integral over a sphere of an electric field (a vector) dot-multiplied by the differential area will give us the flux - which for any sphere can be simplified to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\Phi = \frac{Q_{net}}{\epsilon_0}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;matter-in-electrosatic-fields&quot;&gt;Matter in Electrosatic Fields&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;conductors&quot;&gt;Conductors&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Electrons flow freely inside the metals - they will arrange themselves based on the field applied to the metal&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An electric field applied to a metal will cause the electric field inside the confuctor to become zero, because the electrons will rearrange themselves to form an arrangement where the total field ends up being zero.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Electric Field inside a metal&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;E = 0&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;dialectrics&quot;&gt;Dialectrics&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Electrons don’t flow freely. But they will align or arrange themselves in an orientation based on the electric field applied to the dialectric.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;iclicker-question-concept&quot;&gt;iClicker Question Concept&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We cannot measure the electric field inside of a cynlinder using Gauss’ Law due to the ends of the sphere requiring different integrals than the sides of the cylinder.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;comparison-of-charged-metallic-and-dialectric-spheres&quot;&gt;Comparison of Charged Metallic and Dialectric Spheres&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a uniformly charged dialectric spehere, the electric field inside (and only inside!) the sphere is equal to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;E = \frac{kQr}{R^3}&lt;/script&gt; where &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;r&lt;/script&gt; is the radius of the sphere inside the dialectric and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;R&lt;/script&gt; is the radius of the dialectric.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;R = r&lt;/script&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;E = k\frac{Q}{R^2}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then when the gaussian surface has a radius &lt;em&gt;outside&lt;/em&gt; of the sphere, then the electric field is equal to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;E = \frac{kQ}{r^2}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a conducting spehere where the gaussian surface sphere is inside the conducting sphere:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;E = 0&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For when the radius of the gaussian sphere is greater than the radius of the conducting sphere, the electric field is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;E = \frac{kQ}{r^2}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;faraday-cage&quot;&gt;Faraday Cage&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A piece of metal with a hole in the middle. If the cage is conducting, then the electric field inside the cage is 0.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cavities-no-charge-within-the-cavity&quot;&gt;Cavities (No Charge within the cavity)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;Q_{net} = +Q = Q_{in} + Q_{out}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can find the net surface charge is we place a charge inside a metallic shell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Normally &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;E = 0&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;then &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\Phi = 0&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So then if we put Q in a cavity inside the aphere then we know that the enclosed charge in the cavity will then attract charge to the inside surface of the cavity (within the conductor). This means the leftover charge will be equal to the charge felt on the outside of the sphere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, the charge enclosed in the cavity is equal to the charge on the outsie of the sphere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;september-17th-2015&quot;&gt;September 17th 2015&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lecture-4---electrostatic-potential-energy&quot;&gt;Lecture 4 - Electrostatic Potential Energy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Potentiential Energy &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;= U(r)&lt;/script&gt; - measured in Joules&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Potential &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V(r)&lt;/script&gt; measured in volts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;V(r) = \frac{U(r)}{q_0}&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coulomb’s Law and the Superposition principle are usually sufficient to solve any electrostatic problem. Gauss’ Law simplifies the alculation of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;E&lt;/script&gt; fields for symmetric charge distributions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Say we want to calculate the velocity of two particles. Given the equation we have it would be very difficult because if the electrostatic forces push the particles away from each other, the acceleration changes. Because acceleration changes it would involve solving an integral to obtain the speed. This can be difficult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So instead we can use potential energy to find the kinetic energy, and thus, speed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Remember that the force to move an object from point a to point b is going to be equal to:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;W_{a-b} = F_{a-b} \cdot (b - a)&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Integral Form&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\Delta U(r) = W_{a-b} = \int_{a}^{b} \vec{F} \cdot d\vec{l}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reference Points&lt;/strong&gt; : A matter of convencience, only &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\Delta U&lt;/script&gt; matters (because only forces can be measured and he forces depend on &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\Delta U&lt;/script&gt; not &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;U&lt;/script&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\vec{F}(f) = \frac{\partial U(r)}{\partial r} \hat{r}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;gravitational-and-electrostatic-fields-are-conservative&quot;&gt;Gravitational and &lt;em&gt;Electrostatic&lt;/em&gt; fields are conservative&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason? Both fields are &lt;strong&gt;central&lt;/strong&gt; (a central force depends only on the distance between interacting objects and is directed along the line joining them.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\Delta U&lt;/script&gt; depends only on the &lt;em&gt;initial&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;final&lt;/em&gt; points of the trajectory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For any loop &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\int \vec{F_e} \cdot d\vec{l} = 0&lt;/script&gt; .&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus for our potential energy for any two electrostatic charges&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;electrostatic-potential-energy&quot;&gt;Electrostatic Potential Energy&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;W_{\infty - r} = \frac{q_1q_2}{4\pi\epsilon_0 \cdot r}&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This energy is conservative. Meaning that no matter the path a particle takes from point 1 to point 2 - The change in energy will still be the same!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;from--ur--to--fr-&quot;&gt;From &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;U(r)&lt;/script&gt; to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;F(r)&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\vec{F}(x) = -\frac{dU(x)}{dx}\hat{x}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;september-21st-2015&quot;&gt;September 21st 2015&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;electrostatic-potential&quot;&gt;Electrostatic Potential&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Volts! The electrostatic potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;V(r) = \frac{U(r)}{q}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The electrostatic potential is related to the potential energy of charges in the electric field. Numberically, this is the work done by external forces to bring a positite unit charge from some reference point to the point in question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Units: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{J}{C} =&lt;/script&gt; Volt&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;electric-potential-to-electric-field&quot;&gt;Electric Potential to Electric Field&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\vec{F}(x, y) = -\frac{\partial{U}(x, y)}{\partial x}\hat{x} -\frac{\partial{U}(x, y)}{\partial y}\hat{y}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly the Electric field is equal to the derivative of the electrostatic potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\vec{F}(x, y) = q\vec{E}(x, y)&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;U(x, y) = qV(x, y)&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;calculations-of-electrostatic-potential&quot;&gt;Calculations of Electrostatic Potential&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;V(r) = k\Sigma_i\frac{q_i}{|\vec{r} - \vec{r_i}|}&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;electric-field-and-potential-of-a-charged-ring&quot;&gt;Electric Field and Potential of a Charged Ring&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;V(x) = \frac{1}{4\pi\epsilon_0}\frac{Q}{\sqrt{x^2 + a^2}}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;electric-potential-inside-and-outside-a-conductor&quot;&gt;Electric Potential Inside and Outside a Conductor&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Inside of a (spherical) conductor, the electric potential is equal to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;k\frac{q}{R}&lt;/script&gt; where &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;R&lt;/script&gt; is equal to the radius of the “sphere” conductor.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Outside of a conductor, the electric potential decreases with distance and is equal to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;k\frac{q}{r}&lt;/script&gt;. Where &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;r&lt;/script&gt; is the total distance from the center of the spherical conductor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;september-24th-2015&quot;&gt;September 24th 2015&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lecture-7---capacitors-and-electric-field-energy&quot;&gt;Lecture 7 - Capacitors and Electric Field Energy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a metal we know that the electric field must be perpendicular to the surface of the metal (while the inside of the metal has an electric field of zero).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what about the electric potential distribution over the surface?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The conducting surface is an equipotential surface&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because the E field is 0 everywhere inside a conductor, the electrostatic potential on the surface of a conductor must be equal to the potential everywhere on the surface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The E field in a conductor is always zero!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Electrostatic Potential at any point in the spehere is the same as the potential on the surface!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;capacitors&quot;&gt;Capacitors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A cpacitor is a system of two conducting surfaces (electrodes), the net charge of the two are zero.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is, one plate will be positively charged and the other will be negatively charged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Important!&lt;/em&gt; Because the surfaces are conducting, they are equipotential and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\Delta V = \int^{-electrode}_{+electrode}\vec{E}\cdot d\vec{l}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Capacitance - Is the amount of charge per equipotential. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{Coulombs}{Volts}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Capacitance: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;C = \frac{Q}{\Delta V} = \frac{Q}{\int^{-electrode}_{+electrode}\vec{E}\cdot d\vec{l}}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;capacitance-analogy&quot;&gt;Capacitance Analogy&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bucket Of Water&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;Q&lt;/script&gt; = Amount of Water&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;C&lt;/script&gt; = Amount of water divided by volume of bucket&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\Delta V&lt;/script&gt; = Height of water in bucket&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Capacitance Does not depend on the “amount of charge” really. If we increase the charge on the capacitor, the voltage will also change, meaning the capcitance is constant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;computing-capacitance&quot;&gt;Computing Capacitance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Computing capacitance for a given &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;Q&lt;/script&gt;: Calculate &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\Delta V&lt;/script&gt; and use the definition of capacitance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;E = \frac{\sigma}{\epsilon_0} = \frac{Q}{\epsilon_0A}&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\Delta V = Ed = \frac{Qd}{\epsilon_0A}&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;C = \frac{\epsilon_0A}{d}&lt;/script&gt; (For a parallel Plate capacitor).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;energy-stored-in-a-capacitor&quot;&gt;Energy Stored in a Capacitor&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Final state for a charged capacitor –&amp;gt; E field - &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;Q = \frac{Q}{\epsilon_0A}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work for a capacitor:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;W = \frac{Q^2}{2C}&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;U = \frac{Q^2}{2C} = \frac{CV^2}{2} = \frac{QV}{2}&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;energy-density&quot;&gt;Energy Density&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Valid for almost any point! Very Useful&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;u_E = \frac{1}{2}\epsilon_0E^2&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Total Energy of the electric field&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;U_E = \int_{all space} \frac{1}{2}\epsilon_0E^2(r)d\tau&lt;/script&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Sep 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://zacblanco.github.io//blog/physics/rutgers-physics-227-guide</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://zacblanco.github.io//blog/physics/rutgers-physics-227-guide</guid>
        
        <category>physics</category>
        
        <category>rutgers</category>
        
        <category>fall 2015</category>
        
        <category>electromagnetism</category>
        
        <category>magnet</category>
        
        <category>227</category>
        
        <category>undergraduate</category>
        
        <category>physics.rutgers.edu</category>
        
        <category>electrostatics</category>
        
        <category>dipoles</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A Guide for Principles of EE I at Rutgers University</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we are - a new study guide - for Principles of Electrical Engineering 1 at Rutgers University in the Fall of 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will try to keep this as up to date as possible as the class goes on throughout the semester. Hopefully addressing all topics in the syllabus. The aim is for this to hopefully be able to serve as a study-guide by the time the end of the semester comes around. I hope that this guide will be able to cover all of the topics that are in this course, as well as provide examples of circuits and step-by-step solutions to different problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Course Instructor: Prof. Hana Godrich&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;topics&quot;&gt;Topics:&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Voltage, Current, Resistance&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ohm’s Law, Kirkhoff’s Law&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tools for analyizing circuits&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Node-Voltage Method, Mesh-Current Method
-Thevenin and Norton Equivalents, maximum Power Transfer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Operational amplifiers, inverting, not-inverting and difference amplifier circuits&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Properties of Inductances, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Review of Complex variables - Intro to sinusoidal steady state analysis, sinusoidal sources, Phasors&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Impedance, Admittance, reactance, susceptance, delta-wye simplifications, Phasor Diagrams&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sinusoidal steady sate power calculates, RMS values, frequency selective circuits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;september-3rd-2015&quot;&gt;September 3rd 2015&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;definition-circuit&quot;&gt;Definition: Circuit&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;An interconnection of components or elements that form a &lt;em&gt;closed path&lt;/em&gt; or many closed paths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For any element or component in a circuit, there are at least two terminals (i.e a connection) on each side of the element&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A node is an intersection of &lt;em&gt;two or more&lt;/em&gt; branches or connections off of an element. It can also be thought of as anything that is not part of a component or element.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Circuits can take many different forms - but they can still perform the same function so long as all of the interconnections are the exact same.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A &lt;em&gt;Path&lt;/em&gt; is a single “way” that you can walk through a circuit. Most circuits will have many, many, many paths. They must be continuous - no breaks in the&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A &lt;em&gt;Branch&lt;/em&gt; is a path that moves form one node to another to another. It encompasses only a single element&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;basic-circuit-components&quot;&gt;Basic Circuit Components&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Element or Component&lt;/em&gt;: a two - or more - terminal device in a circuit with behavior described by &lt;em&gt;charactieristics&lt;/em&gt; which vary with time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V&lt;/script&gt; or &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;v&lt;/script&gt; - Voltage. Usually talked about voltage drop or gain over an element or component represented with  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;+&lt;/script&gt; or &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;-&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;I&lt;/script&gt; or  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;i&lt;/script&gt; - Current. Current has a direction chosen &lt;em&gt;almost&lt;/em&gt; arbitrarily by a person analyzing a circuit.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Elements and components don’t have to actually be a &lt;em&gt;part&lt;/em&gt; of the circuit. For example, we can think of a lightbulb as behaving similarly to a resistor. This means in a circuit diagram we can represent the lightbulb simply as a resistor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;more-definitions&quot;&gt;More Definitions&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Essential Node&lt;/em&gt; - A node where three or more circuit elements join&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Essential Branch&lt;/em&gt; - A path that cnnects two essential nodes without passing through an essential node. Must include elements in series. (d-g)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Loop&lt;/em&gt; - a closed path that starts and ends at the same point.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A set of independent loops - Each loop in the set contains at least one branch that is not part of any other loop in the set(a-b-c, b-e-g-d, b-c-f-h-g-d)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mesh&lt;/em&gt; - a loop that does not enclose any other loop (d-b-e-g)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Path&lt;/em&gt; - A trace of connecting basic components or sources with no component or source included (a-b-e-h)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Node&lt;/em&gt; A point (junction) within a circuit where &lt;em&gt;two or more&lt;/em&gt; circuit elements join. (D)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;A set of Indenpendent Loops&lt;/em&gt; - Each loop in the set contains at least one branch that is not part of any other loop in the set&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;!Important!&lt;/em&gt; A network with &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;b&lt;/script&gt; &lt;em&gt;branches&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;n&lt;/script&gt; &lt;em&gt;nodes&lt;/em&gt; and a total of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;l&lt;/script&gt; &lt;em&gt;indenedent loops&lt;/em&gt; will satisfy the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;b = l + n - 1&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Note! The above equation also works for the number of essential branches and essential nodes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See the image below for an explanation
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/ee1-guide/definition-slide-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Circuit and definitions slide&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;september-6th-2015&quot;&gt;September 6th 2015&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;circuit-variables&quot;&gt;Circuit Variables&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Charge: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;q&lt;/script&gt; or &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;Q&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Current: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;i&lt;/script&gt; or &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;I&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Voltage: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;v&lt;/script&gt; or &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Power: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Energy (or work done): &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;w&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;charge&quot;&gt;Charge&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Charge is a property that almost all particles posess.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Like charges repel, and similar charges attract&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There is a minimum unit of charge is denoted by &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;q_e = 1.6 * 10^{-19} C&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Measured in Coulombs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Coloumb’s law: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;F = k\frac{q_1q_2}{r^2}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does this help us???&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Electrical current is actually defined as &lt;em&gt;the flow of positive charge&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It is very important to note that current flow is usually defined as the flow with POSITIVE charge.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;electron-drift&quot;&gt;Electron Drift&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A conducting wire consists of atoms with loosely attached electrons. The electric force from Coulomb’s law causes the loose electrons to jump from atom to atom inside the metal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;electrical-current&quot;&gt;Electrical Current&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;i(t) = \frac{dq(t)}{dt}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The unit &lt;em&gt;Ampere&lt;/em&gt; is what we use to measure current - Also defined as &lt;em&gt;Coulomb’s per second&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;voltage-or-electric-potential-difference&quot;&gt;Voltage or Electric Potential Difference&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;v = \frac{dw}{dq}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The units for &lt;strong&gt;voltage&lt;/strong&gt; is Joules per Coulomb, or &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{J}{C}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Voltage is the energy per unit of charge created by the separation of positive and negative charges&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;So we might also say that voltage is the amount of work required to get a certain amount of charge across two terminals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;direction-for-current-and-voltage&quot;&gt;Direction for Current and Voltage&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/ee1-guide/basic-element-flow.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of basic circuit element with flow&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When creating circuits, it’s very important to note the direction of current and where voltage drops occur.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If we see the current directed into the positive terminal and out of the negative terminal, then we see a &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;voltage drop&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; occur.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If we see current directed into the negative terminal and out of the positive terminal, then we see a &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;voltage gain&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;power&quot;&gt;Power&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Power, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p&lt;/script&gt; is defined as &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{dw}{dt} = iv&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Think about multiplying the units of Voltage and Current&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{Coulomb}{second} * \frac{Joules}{Coulomb} = \frac{Joules}{second}&lt;/script&gt; which is the unit for Power.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In an electric circuit, the total power generated or consumed by elements within the circuit must be equal to 0.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This means that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p_{generated} = p_{consumed}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If power is supplied or generated by an element, another element will supplant/cancel out that element’s power out&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Whenever the current flows in a direction from high potential to low potential (i.e. there is a voltage drop across the element), then the element is &lt;strong&gt;consuming&lt;/strong&gt; the power or energy being delivered to it. (Positive Value&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Whenever the current flows in a direction from low potential to high potential (i.e. there is a voltage rise across the element), then the element is &lt;strong&gt;generating&lt;/strong&gt; the power or energy (Negative Value)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Low potential to high potential: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p = -iv&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;High potential to low potential &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p = iv&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to think of it - is that whichever terminal (positive or negative) the current is flowing into - that is the going to be the sign of the power equation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Current flows into the positive terminal of an element in the circuit –&amp;gt; &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p = iv&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Current flows into the negative terminal of an element in the circuit –&amp;gt; &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p = -iv&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See below for more explanation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;passive-sign-convention&quot;&gt;Passive Sign Convention&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/ee1-guide/passive-sign-convention.png&quot; alt=&quot;Passive Sign Convention Example&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;finding-the-power-consumed-or-delivered-by-an-element&quot;&gt;Finding the power consumed or delivered by an Element&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we have multiple elements in a circuit, we know the voltage drop/rise across each, and the current for all but one element, then we can find the power that is being delivered across the final element. We follow just a few simple steps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For each element, find if the power is consumed or delivered.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For each element calculate the power the is being consumed or delivered.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add all of the power across each element up. Whatever the remaining difference is, the opposite sign (positive/negative) is the amount of power delivered across the last element.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;september-10th-2015&quot;&gt;September 10th 2015&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;unit-2-circuit-components&quot;&gt;Unit 2 Circuit Components&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Topics covered in this Unit:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Inpedendent Source&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Depedent Source&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Passive Circuit Elements&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Resistance and Ohm’s Law&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kirchoff’s Law&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sources Interconnection&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Components Interconnection&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Circuit Modeling and Circuit Analysis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;circuit-components-symbols-ideal-independent-voltage-source&quot;&gt;Circuit Components Symbols: Ideal, Independent, Voltage Source&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Independent Voltage Source&lt;/strong&gt;: Generates a voltage drop across its terminals without relying on other voltages in the circuit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/ee1-guide/voltage-source-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Voltage Source Component&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Independent sources are always marked with a circle&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;An &lt;em&gt;ideal voltage source&lt;/em&gt; supplies the same voltage regardless of current.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Independent Current Source&lt;/strong&gt;: Generates a current through a branch in a circuit without relying on other currents in the circuit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/ee1-guide/current-source-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Current Source Component&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;An &lt;em&gt;ideal current source&lt;/em&gt; supplies the same current regardless of voltage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is very important to note here that the two sources we just introduced do &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; effect the other properties of the circuit. i.e. the independent voltage source will not change anythign about the current, and the independent current source will not change anything about the voltage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dc-direct-current--ac-alternating-current-sources&quot;&gt;DC (Direct Current) &amp;amp; AC (Alternating Current) Sources&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two types current sources that are present in electric current. AC (Alternating current), and DC (direct current). In the images below you can see the difference in these two types of currents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Direct Current&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/ee1-guide/dc-current-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;DC Current Image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alternating Current&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/ee1-guide/ac-current-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;AC Current Image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AC in the United States changes at a frequency at 60Hz. Many other countries in the world use 50Hz.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AC is usually used to transmit power to power plants and so on.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;See chapter 9 for advantages and disadvantages of AC and DC current.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;additional-circuit-sources&quot;&gt;Additional Circuit Sources&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dependent Sources&lt;/strong&gt; Generate a voltage whose value depends on the value of another voltage or current in the circuit. They are usually represented by a diamond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Voltage Controlled Voltage Source (VCVS): &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;v_s = \alpha v_x&lt;/script&gt;
Current Controlled Voltage Source (CCVS): &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;v_s = ri_x&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Note: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\alpha&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;r&lt;/script&gt; are constants&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;v_x&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;i_x&lt;/script&gt; are a specific voltage and a specific current elsewhere in the circuit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Voltage Controlled Current Source (VCCS): &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;i_s = gv_x&lt;/script&gt;
Current Controlled Current Source (CCCS): &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;v_s = \beta i_x&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Note: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;g&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\beta&lt;/script&gt; are constants&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;v_x&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;i_x&lt;/script&gt; are a specific voltage and a specific current elsewhere in the circuit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;interconnection-of-sources&quot;&gt;Interconnection of Sources&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;voltage-sources&quot;&gt;Voltage Sources&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Voltage sources in parallel must be of the same value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A good analogy for voltages changes is that it is a change in elevation. Think of walking up a mountain. If you walk up a mountain 10 meters. Then you walk down 10 meters. You end up at the same elevation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now think of walking up and down the mountain as the change in voltage level instead. Where elevation is the same as voltage change.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Voltage sources of any type can be connected in series. It will step up (or down) the voltage whatever the direction.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Voltage sources in parallel must be of the same value&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;current-sources&quot;&gt;Current Sources&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Current sources connected in series must be of the same value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Current sources connected in parallel are okay. Current flow on the sources essential branch can be maintained without interference.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;passive-circuit-components-symbols&quot;&gt;Passive Circuit Components Symbols&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Passive Circuit Component&lt;/strong&gt;: A device that cannot generate electric energy and does not require external power sources to operate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three types of passive circuit components:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Resistors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Equation: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;v_R = Ri_R&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Capacitor:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Equation: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;i_C = C\frac{dv_C}{dt}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Inductor:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Equation: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;v_L = L\frac{di_L}{dt}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/ee1-guide/passive-circuit-comp-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Passive Circuit Component&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;resistance&quot;&gt;Resistance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resistance&lt;/strong&gt;: The physical property of an element that impedes the flow of current (electron drift)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Represented by &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;R&lt;/script&gt; and is defined by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\rho =&lt;/script&gt; resistivity in &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;ohm\cdot cm&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;l =&lt;/script&gt; length of material in &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;cm&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;A =&lt;/script&gt; cross section of the material in &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;cm^2&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;R = \frac{\rho \cdot l}{A}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The unit of resistance is the &lt;em&gt;Ohm&lt;/em&gt; –&amp;gt; &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\Omega&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ohms-law-linear-model&quot;&gt;Ohm’s Law: Linear Model&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;v= i \cdot R&lt;/script&gt; or &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;i = \frac{v}{R}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the voltage is positive and current flows into the positive terminal, then the current &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;drops&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The voltage, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;v&lt;/script&gt; across and the current, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;i&lt;/script&gt; through a resistance &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;R&lt;/script&gt; that flows down the potential hill&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Power delivered to a resistor: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p = i^2R=\frac{v^2}{R}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note! Power is always &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;consumed&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; by a resistor (&lt;em&gt;positive&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hold up! hold up! I just said that power consumed by a resistor is always positive. How is that possible? What if we switch the positive and negative terminals?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Resistors don’t actually have positive and negative terminals. You can just assume - no matter the orientation or current flow - that they will be consuming power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;september-14-2015&quot;&gt;September 14 2015&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;unit-2-lecture-2&quot;&gt;Unit 2, Lecture 2&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;calculating-power-from-ohms-law&quot;&gt;Calculating Power From Ohm’s Law&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know now that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p = iv&lt;/script&gt;, right? We also know that from Ohm’s law, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;v = iR&lt;/script&gt;. This can then give us a new equation to calculate power based on resistance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;p = iv = i \cdot (iR) = i^2R&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another form is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;p = iv = (\frac{v}{R}) \cdot v = \frac{v^2}{R}&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;open-and-short-circuit-symbols&quot;&gt;Open and Short Circuit Symbols&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In a short circuit the Resistance through between two nodes is 0.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In a closed circuit the resistance between two nodes is &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\infty&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/ee1-guide/open-short-circuit-symbols.png&quot; alt=&quot;Open and Short Ciruit Symbols&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-switch-symbol&quot;&gt;The Switch Symbol&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/ee1-guide/switch-symbol-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Switch Symbol&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Switches can affect the direction the current will flow.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The current will try to take the path of least resistace.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a current can take a path through a circuit that eliminates flow through a resistor, then the current will not flow through to that part of the circuit (or resistor) at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;kirchoffs-laws&quot;&gt;Kirchoff’s Laws&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arguably some of the most important equations in solving circuits come from Kirchoff’s laws. They help us gain information about a circuit to be able to obtain and solve for different component’s quantities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start off with current, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;i&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;kirchoffs-current-law&quot;&gt;Kirchoff’s Current Law&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The algebraic sum of all the currents at any node in a circuit equals zero.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does this mean?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We can pick any nodes in our circuit. A node should always have &lt;em&gt;at least&lt;/em&gt; two currents flowing into it. This means that those two (or more) currents flowing into that node &lt;strong&gt;must&lt;/strong&gt; sum to equal 0.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\Sigma_j i_j = 0&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We &lt;strong&gt;ADD&lt;/strong&gt; currents entering a node. (&lt;em&gt;Postive&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We &lt;strong&gt;SUBTRACT&lt;/strong&gt; currents leaving a node. (&lt;em&gt;Negative&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/ee1-guide/kcl-ex-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;KCL Example 1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now! We are going to see a similar law, but this time it will apply to voltage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;kirchoffs-voltage-law&quot;&gt;Kirchoff’s Voltage Law&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The algebraic sum of all the voltages around any closed path in a circuit equals zero.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what exactly does this mean? It means that we can pick &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; closed loop in the circuit. When we follow that loop we must add (or subtract) the voltages over different elements together to give us a final sum of zero.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the element causes a &lt;em&gt;voltage drop&lt;/em&gt; (positive -&amp;gt; negative), then we &lt;strong&gt;subtract&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the element causes a &lt;em&gt;voltage rise&lt;/em&gt; (negative -&amp;gt; postitive), then we &lt;strong&gt;add&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\Sigma_j v_j = 0&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/ee1-guide/kvl-ex-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;KVL Example 1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Here’s one more example problem you can use to test your calculation skills.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/ee1-guide/kirchoff-ex-prob-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Example Problem 1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mastering these problems takes lots of practice - so it could be beneficial to find more problems online or in a textbook to practice calculating and solving for circuits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;september-21st-2015&quot;&gt;September 21st 2015&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How many KCL and KVL Independent Equations?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;KVL&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;b-n+1&lt;/script&gt; independent loop equations OR &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;b_e - n_e + 1&lt;/script&gt; Is the number of essential branches and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;n_e&lt;/script&gt; is the number of essential nodes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;KCL&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;n - 1&lt;/script&gt; independent node equations OR &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;n_e - 1&lt;/script&gt; if every essential branch has a single current associated with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;steps-to-solve-for-a-circuit&quot;&gt;Steps to Solve for a Circuit&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mark all nodes, resistors, currents, and voltages including direction and polarity.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Choose Nodes for KCL&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Choose Loops for KVL&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Write KCL equations –&amp;gt; &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;n_e - 1 = 3&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;unit-3---simple-resistive-circuits&quot;&gt;Unit 3 - Simple Resistive Circuits&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this unit we’ll address creating circuits that contain resistors in series and parallel - and then finding methods for learning about how to simplify said circuits and then solve for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;resistors-in-series&quot;&gt;Resistors In Series&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Resistors are an element within a circuit - and sometimes these elements are difficult to solve for indicidually. But what we can do is simplify these circuits with multiple of similar elements to make solving these circuits easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Resistors in series mean that the resistors are in a “line” with each other. There are no essential nodes between the two resistors. In this case (where there are no essential nodes) we can simply add the resistances of each resistor together&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;R_{eq} = R_1 + R_2&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From here on our circuit diagrams we can simply just combine the two resistors into one, where the single resistor now has the resistance of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;R_{eq}&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;september-24th-2015&quot;&gt;September 24th 2015&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;simplifying-circuits-with-resistors-in-series-and-parallel&quot;&gt;Simplifying Circuits with Resistors in Series and Parallel&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;resistors-in-series-1&quot;&gt;Resistors in Series&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can simplify resistors that share a single essential node. We know that they are in series if they share an essential node and there are no other elements in between them. We can simply add their resistances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So for resistors in series&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;R_{eq} = R_1 + R_2&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/ee1-guide/res-series-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Resistors in Series&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some notes about simplifying resistors in series&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The current through both resistors is the same. You can prove it using KCL.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The voltage drop is related to the addition of the voltage drop across each individual resistor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;resistors-in-parallel&quot;&gt;Resistors In Parallel&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Resistors in parallel is where two resistors share a node with another branch from an element. To find the equivalent resistance we must use the reciprocal of the resistances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So for resistors in parallel:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\frac{1}{R_{eq}} = \frac{1}{R_1} + \frac{1}{R_2}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;R_{eq} = \frac{R_1R_2}{R_1 + R_2}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/ee1-guide/res-parallel-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Resistors in Parallel&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The equivalent resitance of resistors in parallel will ALWAYS be smaller than the minimum resistance in the set of parallel resistors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-delta-wye-connection&quot;&gt;The Delta-Wye Connection&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the triangular (Delta) configuration - We name the resistors in a very systematic way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For the branch between node a and b, the resistor must be &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;R_c&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For the branch connecting nodes b and c, the resistor must be &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;R_a&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For the branch ocnnection nodes a and c, the resistfor must be &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;R_b&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Wye (Y) configuration&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The (a) node should be connected to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;R_1&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The (b) node should be connected to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;R_2&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The (c) node should be connected to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;R_3&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/ee1-guide/delta-wye-equivalents-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Resistors in Parallel&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This transformation to and from the Delta and Wye (Y) configurations can be useful in analyzing more complex circuits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;september-28th-2015&quot;&gt;September 28th 2015&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;voltage-divider-circuit&quot;&gt;Voltage Divider Circuit&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the first thing we need to know is that if we want to measure the voltage over a resistor, then we need to put the voltmeter in parallel with the resistor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now in a voltage divider circuit, we take that principle and expand on it to divide the voltage by a certain amount by putting multiple resistors in series with one another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The voltage divider contains a voltage source of value &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V_x&lt;/script&gt; and resistors &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;R_1&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;R_2&lt;/script&gt; in series with one another and the voltage source.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know that from KVL the equation for the voltage must be that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;V_x = V_1 + V_2&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From KCL we can find that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;i_x = i_1 = i_2&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and now from KCL and Ohm’s we have&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;i_x = \frac{V_1}{R_1} = \frac{V_2}{R_2}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;we want to now find &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V_1&lt;/script&gt; in terms of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V_x&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;V_1 = f(V_x)&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;V_2 = f(V_x)&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can then find that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V_x = V_1 + \frac{R_2}{R_1}V_1 = (1 + \frac{R_2}{R_1})V_1&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So then solving for &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V_1&lt;/script&gt; we find:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;V_1 = \frac{R_1}{R_1 +  R_2}V_x&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, if we solve for &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V_2&lt;/script&gt;, then&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;V_2 = \frac{R_2}{R_1 + R_2}V_x&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;current-divider-circuits&quot;&gt;Current Divider Circuits&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a current divider circuit we can divide a voltage source’s current by an amount by placing resistors in parallel and putting an ammeter in series with one of the resistors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if we have two resistors in series, then through KVL we have:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;V_x = V_1 = V_2&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and through KCL we have that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;i_x = i_1 + i_2&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And with Ohm’s law included, we can get the equation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;i_1 = \frac{R_2}{R_1 + R_2} i_x&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So then if we solve for &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;i_2&lt;/script&gt; we find that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;i_2 = \frac{}{}i_x&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Sep 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://zacblanco.github.io//blog/electrical-engineering/rutgers-principles-electrical-engineering-1</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://zacblanco.github.io//blog/electrical-engineering/rutgers-principles-electrical-engineering-1</guid>
        
        <category>engineering</category>
        
        <category>rutgers</category>
        
        <category>fall 2015</category>
        
        <category>principles of electrical engineering</category>
        
        <category>guide</category>
        
        <category>class</category>
        
        <category>study</category>
        
        <category>circuits</category>
        
        <category>computer engineering</category>
        
        <category>electrical engineering</category>
        
        <category>engineers</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Quick Tips: XML Schemas and Validation</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A quick side note before the post: I’ve finally started working on for the summer, so I’m hoping that I will be able to write posts more frequently than I did during the semester.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;xml-schemas&quot;&gt;XML Schemas&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What the heck is a schema anyway?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can think of a schema as almost like writing a class in Java. It basically gives us a layout that we want out XML files to follow. It’s basically giving us a blueprint that we want our XML files to conform to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why should I validate my XML files?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well it’s plain and simple. If your program parses XML files, and it needs to file a certain format, you want to make sure that all the files you process are in the correct format. If you don’t validate your files it could break your program. Think of it as like dumping pasta into your toaster oven because you want to cook your pasta. You can’t just cook everything by putting it in the toaster. You have to make sure it’s in the form of a bread first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;All right all right, so I get the point of schemas and validation. How do I validate my files? How do I even write a schema?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well first, we’re going to need to write a schema to validate some kind of xml file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;writing-a-schema&quot;&gt;Writing a Schema&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to make this &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; simple. If you want to learn more about writing schemas check out &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.w3schools.com/schema&quot;&gt;w3 schools’ tutorial on it&lt;/a&gt;. We’re going to write a schema for a person. The person element should contain only 3 simple elements; name, age, and height (in cm). See below for the schema (&lt;code&gt;Person.xsd&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-xml&quot; data-lang=&quot;xml&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;?xml version=&amp;quot;1.0&amp;quot;?&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;

	&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;xs:schema&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;xmlns:xs=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;

		&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;xs:element&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;name=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Person&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
			&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;xs:complexType&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
				&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;xs:sequence&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
					&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;xs:element&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;name=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;name&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;type=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;xs:string&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
					&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;xs:element&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;name=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;age&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;type=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;xs:integer&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
					&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;xs:element&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;name=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;height&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;type=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;xs:integer&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
				&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/xs:sequence&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
			&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/xs:complexType&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/xs:element&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/xs:schema&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;a-quick-note-on-namespaces&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Quick Note on Namespaces&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you notice in the above schema I have prefixed each element with the &lt;code&gt;xs&lt;/code&gt; namespace. This is done to avoid confusion with similar elements over large xml documents that might have conflicting element names. The above document without using namespaces can similarly be written like the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-xml&quot; data-lang=&quot;xml&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;?xml version=&amp;quot;1.0&amp;quot;?&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;

	&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;schema&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;xmlns=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;

		&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;element&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;name=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Person&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
			&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;complexType&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
				&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;sequence&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
					&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;element&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;name=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;name&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;type=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;string&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
					&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;element&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;name=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;age&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;type=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;integer&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
					&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;element&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;name=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;height&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;type=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;integer&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
				&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/sequence&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
			&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/complexType&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/element&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/schema&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whichever way you write the schemas doesn’t matter. If you do have conflicting elements though, it will be beneficial to look more into XML namespaces too. That is not within the scope of this post though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;writing-the-xml-files&quot;&gt;Writing the XML Files&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use eclipse as my IDE and I have set up my project and I have the following folder structure&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;/src/xmlValidator
		/schemas
			/Person.xsd
		/xml
			/Bob.xml
			/Penelope.xml
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that you can see my folder structure let’s write some more files. You should have already created &lt;code&gt;Person.xsd&lt;/code&gt; from the above snippet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s Make a Person. We’ll call the file &lt;code&gt;Bob.xml&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Bob.xml&lt;/code&gt; will contain the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-xml&quot; data-lang=&quot;xml&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;?xml version=&amp;quot;1.0&amp;quot;?&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;Person&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;name&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;Bob&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/name&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;age&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;18&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/age&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;height&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;150&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/height&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/Person&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now here’s &lt;code&gt;Penelope.xml&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-xml&quot; data-lang=&quot;xml&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;?xml version=&amp;quot;1.0&amp;quot;?&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;Person&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;name&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;Penelope&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/name&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;age&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;nineteen&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/age&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;height&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;150.1&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/height&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/Person&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, so now take a look at each of the xml files. Which one do you think is valid? not valid? Pay close attention to the types we defined in our schema.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;main-method-to-check-our-files&quot;&gt;Main Method to Check our Files&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let’s actually write the code to how we can validate our xml files to ensure they follow the schema.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-java&quot; data-lang=&quot;java&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;java.io.File&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;java.io.IOException&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;java.nio.file.Paths&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;javax.xml.*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;javax.xml.transform.stream.StreamSource&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;javax.xml.validation.Schema&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;javax.xml.validation.SchemaFactory&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;javax.xml.validation.Validator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;org.xml.sax.SAXException&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;validator&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;

	&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;static&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;main&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;String&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;[]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;args&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;

		&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;String&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;path&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;System&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;getProperty&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;user.dir&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;/bin&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;String&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;filePath&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;path&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;/xmlValidator/xml/Bob.xml&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;String&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;filePath2&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;path&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;/xmlValidator/xml/Penelope.xml&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;String&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;schemaPath&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;path&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;/xmlValidator/schemas/Person.xsd&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

		&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;File&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;f&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;File&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;filePath&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;File&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;f2&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;File&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;filePath2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;File&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;xsd&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;File&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;schemaPath&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;

		&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;System&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;out&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;println&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;XML file at &amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;getName&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot; is valid: &amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;validateXML&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;xsd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot; for schema &amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;xsd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;getName&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;());&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;System&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;out&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;println&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;XML file at &amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;f2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;getName&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot; is valid: &amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;validateXML&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;xsd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;f2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot; for schema &amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;xsd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;getName&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;());&lt;/span&gt;



	&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;


	&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;static&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;boolean&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;validateXML&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;File&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;xsd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;File&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;xml&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;try&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
			&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;SchemaFactory&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fact&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;SchemaFactory&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;newInstance&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;XMLConstants&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;W3C_XML_SCHEMA_NS_URI&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
			&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Schema&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;s&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fact&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;newSchema&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;xsd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
			&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Validator&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;vdr&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;newValidator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
			&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;vdr&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;validate&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;StreamSource&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;xml&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;));&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;catch&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;IOException&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;SAXException&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;e&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
			&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;System&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;out&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;println&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;e&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;getMessage&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;());&lt;/span&gt;
			&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kc&quot;&gt;false&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kc&quot;&gt;true&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The heart of validation is done within the &lt;code&gt;validateXML()&lt;/code&gt; method. It’s quite simple and it also tells us the errors we receive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem is that once we receive an error, it quits. We don’t find &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of the errors which may or may not be a problem depending on the application. If you notice in the &lt;code&gt;Penelope.xml&lt;/code&gt; file there are two errors, but the program should only return once it finds the first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s simply it. XML Schema validation in a nutshell.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://zacblanco.github.io//blog/markup-language/xml-schema-validation</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://zacblanco.github.io//blog/markup-language/xml-schema-validation</guid>
        
        <category>xml</category>
        
        <category>java</category>
        
        <category>schema</category>
        
        <category>validation</category>
        
        <category>namespaces</category>
        
        <category>markup language</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A (Somewhat) Comprehensive Guide to Physics IB at Rutgers University</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The topics covered in this course are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rotational Dynamics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gravitation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Oscillation and Periodic Motion&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mechanical Waves&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sound&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fluid Mechanics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Temperature and Heat&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thermal Properties of Matter&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The First Law of Thermodynamics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Second Law Of Thermodynamics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The format of this post will be the following: For each equation I will explain the variables used, the typical units used, and any constant values (if they haven’t been defined already). If there are concepts that don’t reside within equations, they will be explained nearest to the equations I feel are most related to that concept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;rotational-dynamics&quot;&gt;Rotational Dynamics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;torque&quot;&gt;Torque&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\tau = Fl = I\alpha&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Torque &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\tau&lt;/script&gt; is equal to the perpendicular force along the moment arm applied a distance, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;l&lt;/script&gt;  from a rotational axis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;kinetic-energy-of-rolling-body&quot;&gt;Kinetic Energy of Rolling Body&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;KE = \frac{1}{2}mv_{cm}^2 + \frac{1}{2}I\omega^2&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The total kinetic energy of a body in rolling motion is equal to the sum of the translational kinetic energy and the rotational kinetic energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;rotational-to-translational-velocity&quot;&gt;Rotational to Translational Velocity&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;v_{cm} = R\omega&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To convert from angular velocity to translational velocity, simply multiply the radius of the object &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;R&lt;/script&gt; by the angular velocity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;rotational-work&quot;&gt;Rotational Work&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;W = \tau\Delta\theta&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The angular version of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W = Fd&lt;/script&gt;. A toque multiple by the distance rotated in radians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;power-of-rotation&quot;&gt;Power of Rotation&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;P = \tau\omega&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The power applied is the angular version of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;P = Fv&lt;/script&gt;. Toque, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\tau&lt;/script&gt; multiplied by the angular velocity, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\omega&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;angular-momentum&quot;&gt;Angular Momentum&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;L = I\omega = rmv\cdot sin(\phi)&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Angular momentum is the angular version of normal momentum. It is equal to the moment of inertia multiplied by its angular velocity. This can also be translated to the normal momentum, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p = mv&lt;/script&gt;, multiplied by the velocity at angle &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\phi&lt;/script&gt; from the perpendicular of the ‘moment arm’ to the object,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;conservation-of-angular-momentum&quot;&gt;Conservation of Angular Momentum&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;I_1\omega_1 = I_2\omega_2&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there is &lt;em&gt;NO&lt;/em&gt; net toque applied to an object, the angular momentum in conserved. That is, th &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;L_1&lt;/script&gt; (initial state) should be equal to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;L_2&lt;/script&gt; (final state).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gravitation&quot;&gt;Gravitation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;gravitational-constant&quot;&gt;Gravitational Constant&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;G = 6.67 \cdot 10^{-11}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is Newton’s constant of gravitation. Used in the equations to follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;graviational-force-of-two-bodies&quot;&gt;Graviational Force of Two Bodies&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;F = \frac{GMm}{r^2}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This equation tells us that two bodies exert the same force on each other based on one object’s mass, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m&lt;/script&gt;, the other object’s mass, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;M&lt;/script&gt;, and the distance between the two objects’ centers of gravity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;potential-energy-of-gravitation&quot;&gt;Potential Energy of Gravitation&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;U = \frac{GMm}{r}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The potential energy of one body with respect to another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;finding--g--on-earth-and-other-planets&quot;&gt;Finding &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;g&lt;/script&gt; on Earth and Other Planets&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;g = \frac{GM_E}{R_E^2}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can find the value for the gravitational acceleration at the surface (or distance from that planet for that matter) so long as we know the planet’s mass, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;M&lt;/script&gt;, and the distance between the object and the center of the planet, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;R&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;circular-orbit-velocity&quot;&gt;Circular Orbit Velocity&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;v_{orbit} = \sqrt{\frac{GM_E}{R}}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can derive this value by setting the values for centripetal force (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{mv^2}{r})&lt;/script&gt; equal to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{GMm}{r^2}&lt;/script&gt;. Solving for v, we find that the velocity in a circular orbit depends only on the mass of the planet and the orbit distance from the &lt;em&gt;center of the planet&lt;/em&gt; (not the surface).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;period-of-orbit&quot;&gt;Period of Orbit&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;T = \frac{2\pi r}{v} = \frac{2\pi r^{\frac{3}{2}}}{\sqrt{GM_E}}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simply the time it takes to make one revolution given velocity v. Second equation is derived from Kepler’s law (see below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;keplers-law-of-equal-areas&quot;&gt;Kepler’s Law of Equal Areas&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{dA}{dt} = rv\cdot sin\phi&lt;/script&gt; s&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../../assets/images/physics-review/kepler-areas.png&quot; alt=&quot;Kepler&#39;s Law of Equal Areas&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kepler’s Law of Equal Areas. In equal units of time, the area a planet sweeps out in a triangle along its orbit path will always be equal to each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;keplers-law-of-orbits&quot;&gt;Kepler’s Law of Orbits&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;T^2 = \frac{4\pi^2a^3}{GM}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This eqation relates the period is takes for a planet to orbit with the semi-major axis, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;a&lt;/script&gt; (or &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;r&lt;/script&gt; if orbit is circular), and the mass of the object, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;M&lt;/script&gt; that a planet or body is orbiting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;total-energy-of-a-body-in-orbit&quot;&gt;Total Energy of a Body in Orbit&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;E_T = -\frac{GMm}{2R}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The total energy for a body in orbit (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;KE + U&lt;/script&gt;) is equal to the above equation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;oscillation-and-periodic-motion&quot;&gt;Oscillation and Periodic Motion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;frequency&quot;&gt;Frequency&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;f = \frac{1}{T}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frequency is defined as the amount of rotations/oscillations per second. units of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;s^{-1}&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;period&quot;&gt;Period&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;T = \frac{1}{f}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The period is simply the inverse of frequency. It is measured in seconds. As in, seconds per oscillation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;angular-frequency&quot;&gt;Angular Frequency&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\omega = 2\pi f&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;angular frequency is a quantity measured in radians per second (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{rad}{s}&lt;/script&gt;). It is used frequently. The magnitude of angular velocity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;hookes-law&quot;&gt;Hooke’s Law&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;F = -kx&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hooke’s law related the force that a spring pulls on an object given a spring’s stiffness (k) and the distance the object is pulled from equilibrium on the spring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;angular-frequency-spring-constant&quot;&gt;Angular Frequency (Spring Constant)&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\omega = \sqrt{\frac{k}{m}}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can calculate the angular frequncy of a mass on a spring by the above equation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;period-of-an-oscillating-object-on-a-spring&quot;&gt;Period of an Oscillating Object on a Spring&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;T = 2\pi\sqrt{\frac{m}{k}}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, because we know &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\omega =  2\pi f&lt;/script&gt;, we can solve for the period too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;total-energy-in-shm&quot;&gt;Total Energy in SHM&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;E_T = \frac{1}{2}mv^2 + \frac{1}{2}kx^2 = \frac{1}{2}kA^2&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The total energy in SHM is equal to the kinetic energy of an object plus its potential energy. This should always sum to a constant value so long as no energy is lost in the system. It should also be equal to the value &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{1}{2}kA^2&lt;/script&gt; because that is the max potential energy when the object is moved from displacement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;maximum-velocity-in-shm&quot;&gt;Maximum Velocity in SHM&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;v_{max} = \omega A&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The maximum velocity for any object in SHM is just the angular frequency multiplied by the amplitude of motion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;maximum-acceleration-in-shm&quot;&gt;Maximum Acceleration in SHM&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;a_{max} = \omega^2A&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The maximum accleration is similar to velocity where it is related to angular frequency and amplitude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;displacement-of-shm&quot;&gt;Displacement of SHM&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;x = A\cdot cos(\omega t + \phi)&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following equation gives us the displacement of any object at time &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;t&lt;/script&gt; in SHM. Because we know that the max value of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;cos\theta&lt;/script&gt; is 1, then the max displacement is the amplitude, A, which it should be. This same concept will follow to the next two equations also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;velocity-of-shm&quot;&gt;Velocity of SHM&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;v = -\omega A\cdot sin(\omega t + \phi)&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because velocity is the derivative of displacement with respect to time, this equation is simply the derivative of the previous one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;acceleration-of-shm&quot;&gt;Acceleration of SHM&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;a = -\omega^2A\cdot cos(\omega t + \phi)&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, similar to the above equation this equation is the derivative of the velocity equation with respect to time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pendulums&quot;&gt;Pendulums&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;simple-pendulums&quot;&gt;Simple Pendulums&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A simple pendulum is a pendulum in which the mass of the string is neglected (or it is too small in comparison to make a noticable difference).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;angular-frequency-simple-pendulum&quot;&gt;Angular Frequency (Simple Pendulum)&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\omega = \sqrt{\frac{g}{L}}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Angular frequency of a simple pendulum is proportional to the gravitational acceleration, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;g&lt;/script&gt; and the length of the pendulum &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;L&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;period-simple-pendulum&quot;&gt;Period (Simple Pendulum)&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;T = 2\pi\sqrt{\frac{L}{g}}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\omega = 2\pi f&lt;/script&gt;, so we can solve for Period and we find that it’s a pretty simple equation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;physical-pendulums&quot;&gt;Physical Pendulums&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Real pendulums are pendulum where all of the mass if &lt;em&gt;NOT&lt;/em&gt; concentrated at the end of the string (or arm). &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m&lt;/script&gt; is the total mass of the pendulum. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;g&lt;/script&gt; is the constant of gravitation. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;d&lt;/script&gt; is the distance from the axis of rotation to the center of gravity of the pendulum. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;I&lt;/script&gt; is the moment of inertia of the whole pendulum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;angular-frequency-physical-pendulum&quot;&gt;Angular Frequency (Physical Pendulum)&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\omega = \sqrt{\frac{mgd}{I}}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Angular frequency for a real pendulum is defined above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;period-physical-pendulum&quot;&gt;Period (Physical Pendulum)&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;T = 2\pi\sqrt{\frac{I}{mgd}}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar to a simple pendulum, we can also solve for period if we know the angular frequency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mechanical-waves&quot;&gt;Mechanical Waves&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;velocity-of-a-wave&quot;&gt;Velocity of a Wave&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;v = \lambda f&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The velocity of any wave is equal to the above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;velocity-of-waves-on-a-string&quot;&gt;Velocity of Waves on a String&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;v =  \sqrt{\frac{F}{\mu}}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can find the velocity of any wave on a string if we know the tension that the string is under, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;F&lt;/script&gt;, and the linear density of the string, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mu&lt;/script&gt;. Linear density is measured in &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{kg}{m}&lt;/script&gt; or &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{mass}{distance}&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;wave-number&quot;&gt;Wave Number&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;k = \frac{2\pi}{\lambda}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simply the equation for wave number.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;displacement-of-a-mechanical-wave&quot;&gt;Displacement of a Mechanical Wave&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;y(x, t) = A\cdot cos(kx - \omega t)&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This equation tells us the vertical displacement, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;y&lt;/script&gt;, from equilibrium of any point on a string moving left to right, given the x position on the string, and the time t, since it oscillating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;principle-of-superposition&quot;&gt;Principle of Superposition&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;y(x, t) = y_1(x, t) + y_2(x, t)&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the principle of superposition. This basically says that any two waves traveling on the same string will sum their displacements together when traveling to form the new displacement from equilibrium&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;displacement-of-2-standing-waves-on-a-string&quot;&gt;Displacement of 2 Standing Waves on a String&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;y(x, t) = 2A\cdot sin(kx)sin(\omega t)&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there are two standing waves on a string, the equation for the displacement from equilibrium become the following.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;average-power-of-a-wave&quot;&gt;Average Power of a Wave&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;P_{ave} = \frac{1}{2}\sqrt{F\mu}\omega^2A^2&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This equation describes the average amount of power used by a string to make a wave with amplitude &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;A&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;fundamental-frequencies-of-a-wave-on-a-string&quot;&gt;Fundamental Frequencies of a Wave on a String&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;f_n = \frac{nv}{2L}; (n=1, 2, 3, ...)&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A wave cannot exist on a string unless half of a wavelength is equal to a multiple of the length of the string. Because a fixed string with tension, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;F&lt;/script&gt; and linear density &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mu&lt;/script&gt; doesn’t change, there are only certain frequencies that can be played on a string. These are called the fundamental frequencies. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;n = 1, 2, 3...&lt;/script&gt;, v is the velocity that the waves travel on the string. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;L&lt;/script&gt; is the length of the string.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sound&quot;&gt;Sound&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;maximum-pressure-of-a-sound-wave&quot;&gt;Maximum Pressure of a Sound Wave&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;P_{max} = BkA&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The maximum pressure of a sound wave depends on Bulk’s modulus, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;B&lt;/script&gt;, the amplitude of the sound, and, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;k&lt;/script&gt;, the wave number.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;velocity-of-a-sound-wave&quot;&gt;Velocity of a Sound Wave&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;v = \sqrt{\frac{B}{\rho}}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The velocity of sound is based on the Bulk modulus of the medium and the density of the medium, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\rho&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;threshold-of-hearing-intensity&quot;&gt;Threshold of Hearing Intensity&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;I_0 = 10^{-12} \frac{W}{m^2}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The threshold of human hearing for sound intensity is equal to the above value. it is a constant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;intensity-in-decibels&quot;&gt;Intensity in Decibels&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\beta = 10dB\cdot log(\frac{I}{I_0})&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Intensity is normally measured on a log scale that we call &lt;em&gt;Decibels&lt;/em&gt;. The equation describes the intensity in decibels using the &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;I&lt;/script&gt; values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;relations-of-sound-intensity&quot;&gt;Relations of Sound Intensity&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;I \propto \frac{1}{r^2} \propto A^2&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sound intensity is proportional to the amplitude of the sound wave being produced and the distance from the source at which the listener hears the sound. That is to double the distance from the source of a sound, you would have an intensity decrease of approximately &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{1}{4}&lt;/script&gt; that of the original.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;fundamental-frequencies-open-pipe&quot;&gt;Fundamental Frequencies (Open Pipe)&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;f_n = \frac{nv}{2L}; (n = 1, 2, 3, ...)&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are fundamental frequencies for sound in open pipes (one with openings at each end). Similar to a string. we need only the speed of sound and the length of the pipe to calculate the fundamental frequencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;fundamental-frequencies-stopped-pipe&quot;&gt;Fundamental Frequencies (Stopped Pipe)&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;f_n = \frac{nv}{4L}; (n = 1, 3, 5, ...)&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar to the above, this equation is for a stopped pipe (one end open, the other closed). We can calculate the fundamental frequncies for any pipe with length L.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See below for visualization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../../assets/images/physics-review/sound-fund-freq.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Fundamental Frequencies in Pipes&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;beat-frequency&quot;&gt;Beat Frequency&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;f_{beat} = f_b - f_a&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two different sound frequencies create what we call ‘beats’. It is addional amplitude variations in the sound we hear. See below image.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../../assets/images/physics-review/beat-freq.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Image of Beat&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;the-doppler-effect&quot;&gt;The Doppler Effect&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;f_L = f_S(\frac{v + v_L}{v + v_S})&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The doppler effect tells us that the frequency a listener hears when they, or a source is moving to or away from the listener changes based on the velocity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;v_L&lt;/script&gt; is positive if the listener moves toward the source.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;v_L&lt;/script&gt; is negative if the listener moves away from the source.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;v_S&lt;/script&gt; is positive if the source moves away from the listener&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;v_S&lt;/script&gt; is negative if the source moves toward the listener&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fluid-mechanics&quot;&gt;Fluid Mechanics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;definition-of-density&quot;&gt;Definition of Density&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\rho = \frac{m}{V}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simply defining density as amount of mass per unit of volume&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;pressure-on-bernoullis-equation&quot;&gt;Pressure (on Bernoulli’s Equation)&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;P = P_0 + \rho gh&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pressure given density of the fluid and changes in height are given by this equation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;definition-of-pressure&quot;&gt;Definition of Pressure&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;P = \frac{F}{A}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We define pressure here as force per unit of area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;definition-of-flow-rate&quot;&gt;Definition of Flow Rate&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\frac{V}{t} = Av&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The flow rate of a fluid is defined by the Volume, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V&lt;/script&gt;, of fluid that passes through a given point in a unit of time, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;t&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;continuity-of-flow-rate&quot;&gt;Continuity Of Flow Rate&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;A_1v_1 = A_2v_2 &gt;&gt; \frac{A_1}{A_2} = \frac{v_2}{v_1}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This equation is basically telling us that for a pipe flowing with an incompressible fluid inside, the velocity multiplied by the cross sectional area should be exactly the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;equal-pressures-and-forces&quot;&gt;Equal Pressures and Forces&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;A_1F_2 = A_2F_1&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This equation relates the cross-sectional area of a pipe and the force pushing against the pipe at two different point on level ground must be equal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;difference-in-pressure-due-to-height&quot;&gt;Difference in Pressure due to Height&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;P_2 - P_1 = -\rho g(y_2 - y_1)&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This equation tells us the difference in pressure to to a change in height, h of the pipe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;bernoullis-equation&quot;&gt;Bernoulli’s Equation&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;p_1 + \rho gh_1 + \frac{1}{2}\rho v^2_1 = p_1 + \rho gh_2 + \frac{1}{2}\rho v^2_2 = constant&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bernoulli’s equation tells us that the pressure and velocity of any two points in a pipe system are related. Remember higher pressure means lower velocity. Lower pressure means higher velocity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;force-of-buoyancy&quot;&gt;Force of Buoyancy&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;F_B = \rho gV&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The force of buoyancy that an object experiences is directly related to the volume of the object submerged in water and the density of the water displaced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Remember&lt;/em&gt;: if an object floats in water, not fully submerged, the bouyant force is still equal to the weight of the object.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;temperature-and-heat&quot;&gt;Temperature and Heat&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;temperature-in-fahrenheit&quot;&gt;Temperature in Fahrenheit&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;T_F = \frac{9}{5}T_C + 32&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This equation is used to convert Temperature in Celsius to Fahrenheit. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;T_F&lt;/script&gt; is the temperature in Fahrenheit and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;T_C&lt;/script&gt; is the temperature in Celsius.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;temperature-in-celsius&quot;&gt;Temperature in Celsius&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;T_C = \frac{5}{9}(T_F - 32)&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This equation is used to convert Temperature in Fahrenheit to Celsius and is simply a re-arraned form of the above equation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;temperature-in-kelvin&quot;&gt;Temperature in Kelvin&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;T_K = T_C + 273&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Temperature on the absolute scale is measured in Kelvins. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;0K&lt;/script&gt; is absolute 0. Other temperature scales can be conerted to Kelvin by the above formula.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;the-ideal-gas-law&quot;&gt;The Ideal Gas Law&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;PV = nRT&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the ideal gas law. In physics we like to use SI units, therefore these quantities are measured in their respective SI units. P is pressure in pascals. V is volume in &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m^3&lt;/script&gt;. n is number of moles of gas. R is equal to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;8.314 \frac{J}{mole\cdot K}&lt;/script&gt;. T is temperature measured in Kelvin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;gas-constant-r&quot;&gt;Gas Constant, R&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;R = 8.314 \frac{J}{mole\cdot K}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just  restatement of value of the gas constant, R.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;R = \frac{PV}{nT}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can rearrange the ideal gas law into this form. We can set two states of a gas equal to each other because we know the gas constant is equal, then we can solve for any changes in values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\frac{T_2}{T_1} = \frac{P_2}{P_1}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A thermometer measures temperature by using the change in pressure that occurs when the temperature rises (or falls) in order to make measurements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;linear-thermal-expansion&quot;&gt;Linear Thermal Expansion&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\Delta L = \alpha L_0\Delta T&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A solid rod will change length with a change in temperature. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\alpha&lt;/script&gt; is a constant different for specific materials that is traditionally measured in &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;(^\circ C)^{-1}&lt;/script&gt; or &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;K^{-1}&lt;/script&gt;. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;L_0&lt;/script&gt; is the inital length of the beam at the initial temperature. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\Delta T&lt;/script&gt; is the change in temperature measured in Celsius or Kelvin&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;thermal-stress&quot;&gt;Thermal Stress&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\frac{\Delta L}{L_0} = \alpha\Delta T&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thermal stress can be simply found by divinding &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;L_0&lt;/script&gt; by the above equation to obtain the thermal stress by a change in temperature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;calories-and-joules&quot;&gt;calories and Joules&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;1 cal = 4.186 \cdot J&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1 calorie is the amount of energy is takes to raise the temperature of 1 gram of water by one degree celsius. This energy is equal to 4.186 Joules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;heat-transfer&quot;&gt;Heat Transfer&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;Q = mc\Delta T&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can find the amount of heat required to change the themperature of the object if we know the specific heat, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;c&lt;/script&gt;, and the mass of the object. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;c&lt;/script&gt; is specific to every material. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\Delta T&lt;/script&gt; is the change in temperature, usually in Kelvin or celsius depending on the units of the specific heat capacity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;total-mass&quot;&gt;Total Mass&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;m = nM&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The total mass of a gas, or material, can be found by multiplying the number of moles, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;n&lt;/script&gt;, and the Molar Mass, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;M&lt;/script&gt;. It is usually measured in &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{g}{mole}&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;Q = nMc\Delta T = nC\Delta T&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Substituting the above equation into the one for heat transfer we find that there is a Molar heat capacity &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;C&lt;/script&gt; which is equal to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;Mc&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;thermal-expansion-in-3-dimensions&quot;&gt;Thermal Expansion in 3 Dimensions&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;B = 3\alpha&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To find a coefficient for volumetric expansion, we can simply multiply a material’s linear expansion constant by 3 to find the value for volumetric expansion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;volumetric-expansion&quot;&gt;Volumetric Expansion&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\Delta V = BV_0\Delta T&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The change in volume of an object due to a change in temperature. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;B&lt;/script&gt; is a constant that we defined above. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V_0&lt;/script&gt; is the inital volume of the object. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\Delta T&lt;/script&gt; is simply the change in temperature, typically in Celsius or Kelvin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;heat-required-for-phase-change&quot;&gt;Heat Required for Phase Change&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;Q = \pm mL&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can calculate the heat required for a phase change of a compound by simply multiplying the mass of the compound by the latent heat of fusion, or latent heat of fusion. Latent heat, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;L&lt;/script&gt; is typically measured in &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{J}{kg}&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;thermal-conductivity&quot;&gt;Thermal Conductivity&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;H = \frac{dQ}{dt} = kA\frac{T_H - T_C}{L}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rate of heat transfer between a hot and cold resevoir is equal to the change in heat, or energy, over a period of time. This means the value is measured in Watts. We can calculate the power flowing through an object by using its thermal conductivity, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;k&lt;/script&gt;, the cross-sectional area that the heat is flowing through, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;A&lt;/script&gt;. The Temperatures of each hot and cold resevoir respectively measured in &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;K&lt;/script&gt;. and the length of the heat conductor, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;L&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;heat-radiation&quot;&gt;Heat Radiation&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;H = Ae\sigma T^4&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every body emits some kind of electromagnetic radiation. The amount of power that a body emits is equal to its surface area, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;A&lt;/script&gt; multipled by its emmisivity, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;e&lt;/script&gt;, the Stefan-Boltzmann constant, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\sigma&lt;/script&gt;, and the temperature of the body in Kelvin. However, note that this equation is valid if the body and its surrounding environment are of the same temperature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\sigma = 5.6704 \cdot 10^{-8} \frac{W}{m^2\cdot K^4}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the constant value of the Stefan-Boltzmann constant, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\sigma&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;H = Ae\sigma(T^4 - T_S^4)&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a body and it’s surrounding temperature are not the same, then we can find the power emitted by a body by the above equation where &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;T_S&lt;/script&gt; is the temperature of the surroundings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;thermal-properties-of-matter&quot;&gt;Thermal Properties of Matter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;the-ideal-gas-law-again&quot;&gt;The Ideal Gas Law (Again)&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;PV = nRT&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just iterating over the gas law again. Make sure you know it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;relation-between-pv-and-the-translational-kinetic-energy-of-a-gas&quot;&gt;Relation Between PV and the Translational Kinetic Energy of a Gas&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;PV = \frac{2}{3}K_{TR}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;K_{TR}&lt;/script&gt; is the Average translational kinetic energy of a gas. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;PV&lt;/script&gt; is equal to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{3}{2}&lt;/script&gt; this value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;average-translational-kinetic-energy&quot;&gt;Average Translational Kinetic Energy&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;K_{TR} = \frac{3}{2}nRT&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The average translational kinetic energy of an entire gas is equal to this. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;nRT&lt;/script&gt; are their respective values from the ideal gas law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;molar-mass&quot;&gt;Molar Mass&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;M = N_Am&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mass of one molecule of a gas can be found by dividing the Molar Mass, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;M&lt;/script&gt; by Avogadro’s number, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;N_A&lt;/script&gt;. It is equal to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;6.022 \cdot 10^{23}&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;average-kinetic-energy-of-a-gas&quot;&gt;Average Kinetic Energy of a Gas&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\frac{1}{2}M(v^2)_{ave} = \frac{3}{2}RT&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can relat the average kinetic energy of molecule of a gas by the values of R and T and its Molar Mass&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;average-kinetic-energy-of-a-molecule-molar-mass&quot;&gt;Average Kinetic Energy of a Molecule (Molar Mass)&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;k = \frac{R}{N_A} = 1.381\cdot 10^{-23}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Boltzmann constant, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;k&lt;/script&gt;, is simply equal to the gas constant, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;R&lt;/script&gt; divided by Avogadro’s Number.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;average-kinetic-energy-of-a-molecule-mass&quot;&gt;Average Kinetic Energy of a Molecule (Mass)&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\frac{1}{2}m(v^2)_{ave} = \frac{3}{2}kT&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we know the mass of the gas, then the average kinetic energy of a molecule is simply the above equation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;root-mean-square-speed-of-a-molecule&quot;&gt;Root-Mean Square Speed of a Molecule&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;v_{rms} = \sqrt{v_{rms}^2} = \sqrt{\frac{3kT}{m}} = \sqrt{\frac{3RT}{M}}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can calculate the average velocity of a gas particle by the above equations. Remember &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m&lt;/script&gt; is just the normal mass of the gas, while &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;M&lt;/script&gt; is the Molar mass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;heat-capacities&quot;&gt;Heat Capacities&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the theory behind the kinetic energy of a particle, we can estimate the heat capacities of simple gases that have &lt;em&gt;constant volume&lt;/em&gt;. It is important that we note this is with constant volume.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;monatomic-gas&quot;&gt;Monatomic Gas&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;C_V = \frac{3}{2}R&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a monatomic gas, this is simply the heat capacity&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;diatomic-gas&quot;&gt;Diatomic Gas&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;C_V = \frac{5}{2}R&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a diatomic gas (two atoms per molecule) the heat capacity is &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{5}{2} R&lt;/script&gt; which is because we add rotational degrees of freedom to the molecule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;monatomic-solid&quot;&gt;Monatomic Solid&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;C_V = 3R&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a solid that has molecules of only 1 atom, the heat capacity at constant volume is only &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;3R&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;E_T = 3nRT&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The total Energy of a solid is equal to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;3nRT&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;phase-diagrams&quot;&gt;Phase Diagrams&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../../assets/images/physics-review/phase-diag.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of Phase Diagram&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phase diagrams can be useful in determining the conditions under which a material transitions phases from solid, to liquid, and gas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The figure denotes the curves which show melting, freezing, vaporization, condensation, sublimation, and deposition. Each area shows the different phases that occur given certain temperature and pressure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The triple point is the point at which all 3 states of matter can exist for a certain material. The critical point is the point at which the properties of liquids and gases mix due to high pressure and temperature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-first-law-of-thermodynamics&quot;&gt;The First Law of Thermodynamics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;W = \int_{V_1}^{V_2}pdV&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The amount of work done by a gas at pressure, p, is equal to the integral from one volume to another of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p&lt;/script&gt;.  This is the general equation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;W = p(V_2 - V_1)&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At constant pressure, the work done is simply the pressure (in pascals), multipled by the difference of the two states of volume.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;W = nRT\cdot ln(\frac{V_2}{V_1}) = nRT\cdot ln(\frac{p_1}{P_2})&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To derive this, from the ideal gas law, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;P = \frac{NRT}{V}&lt;/script&gt;. If we replace P with this value in our integral, we find that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W = nRT \int_{V_1}^{V_2} \frac{dV}{V}&lt;/script&gt;. This is how we find the equation. All units are in SI. Also, because &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{V_2}{V_1} = \frac{p_1}{p_2}&lt;/script&gt;, we get the second form of this equation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-first-law-of-thermodynamics-1&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The First Law of Thermodynamics&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;U_2 - U_1 = \Delta U = Q - W&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is considered &lt;em&gt;The First Law of Thermodynamics&lt;/em&gt;. It is essential to understand this. Basically this equation related the amount of heat added to (or lost) by a gas, and the amount of work done on/by the gas. We can find the change in internal energy between any two states by this equation. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\Delta U&lt;/script&gt; is the change in internal energy between two states. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;Q&lt;/script&gt; is the amount of heat added or lost by a gas. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W&lt;/script&gt; is the amount of work. It is important to note the sign convention. Adding heat to a gas denotes &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;+Q&lt;/script&gt;. Taking heat away is &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;-Q&lt;/script&gt;. Work done &lt;em&gt;by the gas&lt;/em&gt; denotes &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;+W&lt;/script&gt;. If the work is done &lt;em&gt;on the gas&lt;/em&gt;, then we have &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;-W&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\Delta U = Q - p\Delta V&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If gas is at a constant pressure and volume is changing, we know that the &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W = p\Delta V&lt;/script&gt; so that gives us this equation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\Delta U = nC_V\Delta T&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a gas at constant volume and a changing temperature (isobaric), we can relate a small change in the internal energy &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\Delta U&lt;/script&gt; to the Molar heat capacity at constant volume&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;adiabatic-process&quot;&gt;Adiabatic Process&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\Delta U = -W&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In n adiabatic process, heat is not lost or gained, therefore the change in internal energy is simply the work done by the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;isochoric-process&quot;&gt;Isochoric Process&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\Delta U = Q&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An isochoric process means that there is no change in volume. If there is no change in volume, then the system can’t be doing any work, which means &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W = 0&lt;/script&gt;. Therefore our change in internal energy must only be the heat added to the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;isobaric-process&quot;&gt;Isobaric Process&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;W = p\Delta V&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an isobaric process, the pressure is constant, which means we can relate the amount of work done by a gas to be &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p\Delta V&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;isothermal-process&quot;&gt;Isothermal Process&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\Delta U = 0 \therefore Q = W&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an isothermal process there is no change in the temperature of the system. Therefore is there isn’t a change in the temperature, then the change in internal energy &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\Delta U = 0&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;heat-capcity-at-a-constant-pressure&quot;&gt;Heat capcity at a constant pressure&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;C_p = C_V + R&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We find the molar heat capacity for a gas at constant pressure (not volume) is simply equal to its molar heat capacity at constant volume plus the gas constant, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;R&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;ratio-of-heat-capacities&quot;&gt;Ratio of Heat Capacities&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\gamma = \frac{C_p}{C_V}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\gamma&lt;/script&gt; is the ratio of heat capacities which is simply the molar heat capacity at constant pressure over the molar heat capacity at constant volume.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;work-done-in-adiabatic-processes&quot;&gt;Work Done in Adiabatic Processes&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;W = nC_V(T_1 - T_2)&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an adiabatic process we can find the work done by a gas to be equal to the number of moles of the gas, multipled by the molar heat capacity at constant volume multiplied byh the change in temperature from two states, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\Delta T&lt;/script&gt;. Note that temperature should be in Kelvin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;W = \frac{C_V}{R}(p_1V_1 - p_2V_2)&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again in an adiabatic process we rearrange what we have above we can find that the work done over two states is equal to the &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;C_V&lt;/script&gt; multiplied by the pressures and volumes at each state of the gas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-second-law-of-thermodynamics&quot;&gt;The Second Law Of Thermodynamics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any device that can turn heat into Work, is called a &lt;em&gt;heat engine&lt;/em&gt;. All engines absorb heat form some resevoir at a higher temperature, use that heat to do work, and discard some heat at a lower temperature. That is the net heat &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;Q&lt;/script&gt; of a engine process is equal to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W&lt;/script&gt;. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;Q = W&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can visualize he cycle with the following image:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../../assets/images/physics-review/carnot-cycle.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Image of Carnot Cycle&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;net-heat-absorbed-in-an-engine-cycle&quot;&gt;Net Heat Absorbed in an Engine Cycle&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;Q = |Q_H| - |Q_C|&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the amount of heat that is transferred into work. Because &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;Q = W&lt;/script&gt;, the amount of work done in an engine cycle is the difference of the absolute values of the heats &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;Q_C&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;Q_H&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;thermal-efficiency-of-an-engine&quot;&gt;Thermal Efficiency of an Engine&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;e = \frac{W}{Q_H} = 1 + \frac{Q_C}{Q_H} = 1 - \left|\frac{Q_C}{Q_H}\right|&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because we know from above that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;Q_C&lt;/script&gt; can never be zero, this means that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W&lt;/script&gt; is always less than &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;Q_H&lt;/script&gt;. This leaves us with the fact that our engine efficiency, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;e&lt;/script&gt; &lt;em&gt;MUST&lt;/em&gt; be less than 1. It is impossible to have an efficiency of 1 or greater.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;thermal-efficiency-in-an-otto-cycle&quot;&gt;Thermal Efficiency in an Otto Cycle&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;e = 1- \frac{1}{r^{\gamma - 1}}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\gamma&lt;/script&gt; is defined as the ratio of heat capacities at constant volume and pressure (see earlier).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../../assets/images/physics-review/otto-cycle.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of Otto Cycle&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above is an image detailing a &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;pV&lt;/script&gt; diagram of a normal Otto Cycle. From A to B there is an adiabatic compression (no heat lost). B to C we have heat added into the system with constant pressure and some volume change (This means some work is done). Point C to D there is the power stroke. The gas expands at somewhat constant temperature doing as much work as is can while pressure decreases. Then from point D to A the extra heat is exhausted as the gas cools in temperature. It also drops in pressure while volume remains constant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;work-and-heat-in-refrigeration&quot;&gt;Work and Heat in Refrigeration&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;|Q_H| = Q_C + W&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can think of a refrigerator as simply a heat engine, but reversed. Instead of the hot resevoir letting heat out to do work, a refrigerator will have a cold resevoir, add work into the system, and exhaust more heat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;efficiency-of-refrigeration&quot;&gt;Efficiency of Refrigeration&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;K = \left|\frac{Q_C}{W}\right| = \left|\frac{Q_C}{Q_H - Q_C}\right|&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;efficiency-of-refrigeration-form-2&quot;&gt;Efficiency of Refrigeration (Form 2)&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;K = \frac{H}{P}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;stating-the-second-law-of-thermodynamics&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Stating the Second Law of Thermodynamics&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It is impossible for any system to undergo a pocess in which it absorbs heat from a resevoir at a single temperaure and converts the heat completely into mechanical work, with the system ending in the same state in which is began.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can also state it as: &lt;em&gt;It is impossible for any process to have as its sole result the transfer of heat form a cooler to a hotter body.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;steps-of-the-carnot-cycle&quot;&gt;Steps of the Carnot Cycle&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../../assets/images/physics-review/carnot-diag.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Carnot Diagram&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The gas expands isothermally at Temperature &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;T_H&lt;/script&gt; absorbing heat &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;Q_H&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It expands adiabatically until its temperature drops to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;T_C&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is compressed isothermally at &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;T_C&lt;/script&gt; rejecting heat &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;Q_C&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is compressed adiabatically back to its inital state at tempterature &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;T_H&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;efficicency-of-a-carnot-engine&quot;&gt;Efficicency of a Carnot Engine&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;e_{Carnot} = 1 - \frac{T_C}{T_H} = \frac{T_H - T_C}{T_H}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;T_C&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;T_H&lt;/script&gt; are the temperatures of the cold and hot resevoirs respectively. However, it is important to note that all temperatures should be measured in &lt;em&gt;Kelvin&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;efficiency-through-refrigeration&quot;&gt;Efficiency Through Refrigeration&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;K_{Carnot} = \frac{T_C}{T_H - T_C}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar to the efficiency of a carnot engine, the temperatures for the efficiency of refrigeration must also be measured in Kelvin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;entropy&quot;&gt;Entropy&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\Delta S = \frac{Q}{T}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a reversible isothermal process, the entropy is measured as above. It has units of Energy / Temperature which normally is &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{J}{K}&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;entropy-restated&quot;&gt;Entropy Restated&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\Delta S = \int_1^2\frac{dQ}{T}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;entropy-in-non-isothermal-processes&quot;&gt;Entropy in Non-Isothermal Processes&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a process which isn’t isothermal we can’t use the above equations. The equation to use is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\Delta S = \int_{T_1}^{T_2}mc\frac{dT}{T} = mc\cdot ln(\frac{T_2}{T_1})&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://zacblanco.github.io//blog/physics/physics-IB-review</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://zacblanco.github.io//blog/physics/physics-IB-review</guid>
        
        <category>physics</category>
        
        <category>rutgers</category>
        
        <category>spring 2015</category>
        
        <category>final review</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Neural Networks and the Backpropagation Algorithm</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The other day I had been looking up information on &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Machine_learning&quot;&gt;machine learning&lt;/a&gt;. I’m new to some of the topics in this field but I have been introduced to them before. I’ve always wanted to learn more. The idea of teaching a computer how to “learn” just seems intriguing to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Specifically I had been researching &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Artificial_neural_network&quot;&gt;neural networks&lt;/a&gt;. They are useful because they can help uncover hidden patterns in a plethora of data, or be taught to perform certain tasks such as handwriting or facial recognition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had watched an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=q0pm3BrIUFo&quot;&gt;MIT OpenCourseWare Lecture&lt;/a&gt; which gave a rough introduction to neural networks which I found to be quite captivating. I found it so fantastic actually that I wanted to share the basic concepts here. For the purpose of this post, I’m going to assume that we’re teaching this neural net via supervised learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, we are going to make this neural network learn by giving it a set of “correct” input and output values, which it will use to calibrate, or change its own structure to make sure that it also outputs the correct values. Let’s dive in!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To explain briefly, neural networks are modeled after the same neurons that exist in our brain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/b/b5/Neuron.svg/500px-Neuron.svg.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of Neuron&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For our purpose we are going to focus on only a few of the main features of a neuron which are critical to the model of neuron.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main parts that we are going to focus on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dendrites&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Axon&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Axon Terminals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The dendrites&lt;/strong&gt; are small tree-like structures that are stimulated when enough neurotransmitters are dumped into the synapse between a neuron and the end of the dendrite. Some of these dendrites might be easier to stimulate than other based on various factors&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The axon&lt;/strong&gt; is the lengthy part of the neuron which simply propagates a “spike” of energy to the axon terminals, which originates from the dendrites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The axon terminals&lt;/strong&gt; dump neurotransmitters into the synapse to help stimulate the dendrites of the next neuron.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of each &lt;em&gt;axon terminal&lt;/em&gt; there exists another neuron’s dendrites separated by a tiny gap of space called the &lt;strong&gt;synapse&lt;/strong&gt;. When a neuron is stimulated, it will dump neurotransmitters into the synapse. If there are enough neurotransmitters dumped into the synapse, It will stimulate the next neuron’s dendrites, sending a spike of “excitement” or “energy” to the next neuron, and so forth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can imagine some synapses being smaller or larger, needing more or less neurotransmitters to excite a neuron.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a gross simplification of a neuron, but for the model of a neural network, we don’t need to understand more than this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;modeling-the-neuron&quot;&gt;Modeling the Neuron&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/neural-nets/net-model.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Image of Model&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, notice the inputs. Each input from &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;x_1&lt;/script&gt; to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;x_n&lt;/script&gt; is given as an input to the neuron. Each of the inputs is multiplied by a weight &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;w&lt;/script&gt; corresponding to an input before being summed into the function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The neuron also has a bias, labeled  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;b&lt;/script&gt; in the diagram, which I like to call &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;w_0&lt;/script&gt;. We can think of this bias as a given input to each neuron that always has a value of -1. The weight of the bias input &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;w_0&lt;/script&gt; can be adjusted accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think of each input multiplied by a weight representing a neurotransmitter that is dumped into a synapse between neurons by one of the axon terminals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From here we can represent the total stimulus as the sum of each input multiplied by a corresponding weight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;-w_0 + \sum_{i=1}^{n}x_iw_i&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The value of this will be then be passed onto the activation, or &lt;em&gt;threshold&lt;/em&gt; function. The threshold function might be best viewed as a single-step function, where say once the input &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\alpha&lt;/script&gt; reaches a certain value, it will output a certain value. We’re going to keep this to ones and zeros.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/neural-nets/threshold-med.png&quot; alt=&quot;Threshold Example&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This part is where the dendrites need to pick up enough neurotransmitter signals to send that spike of “energy” or “excitement” down its axon to the axon terminals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, once the threshold is activated or not, we will get an output from this neuron. We can string many neurons together and in different patterns with different layers to create a network. More complex networks take up more computational power, but they can also convey more complex functions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we create and run a test using our own neural network, we are going to need to find out how good (or bad) the neural network did at calculating our answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember how I said that the neural network is given a set of “correct” inputs and outputs to learn from? Well here’s where that comes into play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say that our output of the neural net is &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;z&lt;/script&gt; and our desired or &lt;em&gt;correct&lt;/em&gt; output is going to be assigned to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;d&lt;/script&gt;. We are going to need a function to test our performance of the neural network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s call this function &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;P&lt;/script&gt;. Also, for simplicity’s sake, and because this is &lt;em&gt;convenient&lt;/em&gt; we’re going to make the performance function the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;P(d, y) = -\frac{1}{2}(d-z)^2&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(&lt;em&gt;You’ll see what I mean by convenient later&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;adjusting-the-model&quot;&gt;Adjusting the Model&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now we’ve got this model. We have a function to test whether our output is close to what we want it to be. We have a way to add our inputs together. What comes next?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, we need to have some way of adjusting the neuron to make sure we get closer to our desired output. But how do we know what to adjust? and by how much?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re going to use a method called &lt;strong&gt;gradient descent&lt;/strong&gt; (or &lt;em&gt;ascent&lt;/em&gt; depending on direction). This will help us determine which direction we need to move our weights in to get closer to the desired value, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;d&lt;/script&gt;. Be prepared for lots of math.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we know that our desired outputs &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;d&lt;/script&gt; can be given by &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\overline{d} = g(\overline{x})&lt;/script&gt;; where &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\overline{d}&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\overline{x}&lt;/script&gt; are our vectors of inputs and desired outputs that our neural network is going to learn from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem is that we don’t know what function &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;g&lt;/script&gt; is, which is why we’re using the neural network to represent it. With the neural networks, we can represent our inputs and outputs by a multivariate function &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;f&lt;/script&gt;. This function can be represented by &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\overline{y} = f(\overline{x}, \overline{w})&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given these functions, we can see our performance function is now&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;P(g(\overline{x}), f(\overline{x}, \overline{w})) = -\frac{1}{2}(g(\overline{x})-f(\overline{x}, \overline{w}))^2&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can see from here the performance function is really just a function of the inputs, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;x&lt;/script&gt; and the weights &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;w&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now imagine that we add some complexity to our neural network. We are going to chain together multiple neurons to create layers. We can then chain these layers together. The more chains and connections between neurons the more complex are the things we can model or predict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mathematically speaking for this network we have vectors &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\overline{x}&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\overline{w}&lt;/script&gt; for each layer. The individual values of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\overline{w}&lt;/script&gt; are the values we modify in our network to conform the inputs to the desired outputs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just imagine the above diagram of the neural network laid end to end and on top of each other. A general overview can be seen below, where each circle represents a neuron:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/4/46/Colored_neural_network.svg/300px-Colored_neural_network.svg.png&quot; alt=&quot;Model of Neural Net&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where things start to become more interesting. Using the algorithm of gradient descent, we can alter the weights &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\overline{w}&lt;/script&gt; by taking the gradient of our performance function with respect to each weight. We can also multiply this gradient by a rate constant, let’s say &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\delta&lt;/script&gt;, that will determine how much we alter the weights over each iteration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let’s look at our formula&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\triangle w = \delta\nabla_w P = \delta\langle \frac{\partial P}{\partial w_0}, \frac{\partial P}{\partial w_1}, \cdot\cdot\cdot, \frac{\partial P}{\partial w_n} \rangle&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is now telling us that the change in our &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;w&lt;/script&gt; over each iteration is going to be equal to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\delta&lt;/script&gt; multiplied by the partial derivative of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;P&lt;/script&gt; with respect to each weight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But wait! We have a problem here. We can’t just simply take the partial derivative of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;w&lt;/script&gt; with respect to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;P&lt;/script&gt; because &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;w&lt;/script&gt; lies within our other function &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;f&lt;/script&gt;. This means that we are going to need the chain rule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this brings up another problem: because we are going to need to take all these derivatives all of the functions in our neural network &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; be differentiable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the problem of differentiability lies within our step function. Because a step function is not differentiable we need another function to replace this. Fortunately there is one similar to it that &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; differentiable!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s called a sigmoid function. You might have seen it before. It has the form&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;S(\alpha) = \frac{1}{1 + e^{-\alpha}}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This function also happens to be &lt;em&gt;convenient&lt;/em&gt;. (You’ll see why in a second)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The graph of the sigmoid has the following shape:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/neural-nets/sigmoid.png&quot; alt=&quot;Sigmoid function&quot; /&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Great! So where do we go from here?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I suggest you watch the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=q0pm3BrIUFo&quot;&gt;video I linked earlier&lt;/a&gt; if you want a really good understanding of how this works. I will do my best to explain it, but I won’t go into explicit detail of how this all works together. The video will explain things more thoroughly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if we keep taking our partial derivatives with the chain rule, it turns out that we will need to take the derivative of this sigmoid function and the performance function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sigmoid function just so happens to be pretty neat. Let’s call it &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\beta&lt;/script&gt;. If you take the derivative of this function &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; we manipulate it a bit, that the derivative of the sigmoid turns out to be expressed in terms of the original function itself. I’ll let the math do the talking here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\beta = \frac{1}{1 + e^{-\alpha}}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\frac{d}{d\alpha}(\beta) = (1 + e^{-\alpha})^2 e^{-\alpha}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we rearrange our derivative a little bit:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\frac{d}{d\alpha}(\beta) = \beta(1-\beta)&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Voila! The derivative of the sigmoid function turns out to be given in terms of the original! I find that to be quite astounding. If you don’t believe me you’ll just have to take my word for it. I promise you it works. (This is also why I called this function &lt;em&gt;convenient&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now lets do the derivative of the performance function, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;P&lt;/script&gt;. We need to take the derivative with respect to the neuron’s output, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;y&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s pretty simple, so I’m not going to go into it, but &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{\partial P}{\partial y} = (d - y)&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it turns out to be a pretty simple derivative, which is why this function just so happens to be &lt;em&gt;convenient&lt;/em&gt; for our purposes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;calculating-the-change-via-backpropagation&quot;&gt;Calculating The Change via Backpropagation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Calculating the change for each weight isn’t as simple as a single derivative as the neurons in a hidden layer put a bunch of junk in the way, so we end up needing the chain rule. That math can get pretty messy, so I’m going to do my best to simplify it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So just as a refresher, let’s look at what we need to calculate. Remember than &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;w_0...w_n&lt;/script&gt; represents just the weights of a single neuron. We have to calculate the adjusted weights for every neuron of each layer in our neural network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\triangle w = \delta\nabla_w P = \delta\langle \frac{\partial P}{\partial w_0}, \frac{\partial P}{\partial w_1}, \cdot\cdot\cdot, \frac{\partial P}{\partial w_n} \rangle&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start by considering the neurons in the very last layer of the network, the output neurons. These require the least amount of work to calculate because we simply need the derivative of the perfomance function, the derivative of the sigmoid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\gamma_{n}&lt;/script&gt; where n represents an arbitrary number between &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;0&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;N&lt;/script&gt; for each neuron. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;y_n&lt;/script&gt; is the output of the threshold function from the neuron on layer &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;L&lt;/script&gt; where, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;L&lt;/script&gt; represents the network layer on which variable lies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\gamma_{n}&lt;/script&gt; will be equal to the following if it is an output neuron. Remember &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;z&lt;/script&gt; is the final output and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;d&lt;/script&gt; is desired output.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\gamma_{n} = y_n^{L}(1 - y_n^{L})(d - z)&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and if gamma is an inner or “hidden layer” neuron&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\gamma_{n} = y_n^{L}(1 - y_n^{L})\sum_{n=0..N}\gamma^{L+1}_n w_n&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now that we have &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\gamma_n&lt;/script&gt;, the change in weight for a given neuron on the output layer is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\triangle w = \delta y_{n}^{L-1}\gamma_n&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;wrapping-up&quot;&gt;Wrapping Up&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what does all of this mean?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we take a look at the math, starting at the output neurons, we calculate their &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\gamma_n&lt;/script&gt; values which rely on the network’s output. We can do this fairly quickly for our output layer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we’ll move another layer closer to the starting point of our network. The change in their weights for the networks depends on the &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\gamma_n&lt;/script&gt; of the layer in front of it, which we happened to have already calculated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What this means is that when we are calculating exactly how to adjust the weights in our neural network, the change in each weight depends on a few things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The input to the neuron&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The output of the neuron&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The weight of the neurons in the layers closer to the output.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This helps explain why it’s called the backpropagation algorithm. You need to calculate the change in weights at the end of your neural network before you can calculate the change in the beginning. So you work your way back in a wave-like manner, hence the name &lt;em&gt;backpropagation&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other great thing about this algorithm is that the change in weight depends on things you’ve already calculated, &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; things you’re going to have to calculate anyways. It’s extremely effecient. There are few, if any, wasted computations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s simply it. The most basic of neural networks and the backpropagation algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;credits&quot;&gt;Credits&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This whole post was a learning experience for me, so I feel I should give credit where credit is due.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=q0pm3BrIUFo&quot;&gt;MIT Lecture, inspiration for this post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Backpropagation&quot;&gt;Wikipedia page on the backpropagation algorithm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/7412214/Explanation_1.pdf&quot;&gt;PDF from Caltech&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wikimedia for some images&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For any corrections to this post, please leave a comment.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://zacblanco.github.io//blog/machine-learning/neural-networks-and-backpropagation</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://zacblanco.github.io//blog/machine-learning/neural-networks-and-backpropagation</guid>
        
        <category>neural networks</category>
        
        <category>machine learning</category>
        
        <category>AI</category>
        
        <category>artificial intelligence</category>
        
        <category>MIT</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hosting your Jekyll site with GitHub Pages</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As a continuation to the series of the last few posts I will be explaining how to host your jekyll site for &lt;strong&gt;free&lt;/strong&gt; using &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;. GitHub provides completely free website hosting using your own GitHub account. For more information I suggest reading up on &lt;a href=&quot;https://pages.github.com/&quot;&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First off, you’re going to need to &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/join&quot;&gt;create an account on GitHub&lt;/a&gt; if you haven’t already. GitHub is a fantastic site that can host private and public git repositories for your personal projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a list of a few advantages to using GitHub Pages:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Completely Free&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A site for every project&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use your own domain name&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Completely integrated with Git&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course some disadvantages:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;No server side scripting&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;No control over how the site is served&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;No secure connections with &lt;code&gt;https&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now this really isn’t a complete list, but these are some of the things I thought would stand out to most people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now for the fun part! Let’s get started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;create-a-repository-for-your-site&quot;&gt;Create a Repository for Your Site&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First make sure that you’re logged in to GitHub. Then, head over to your GitHub profile located at &lt;code&gt;https://github.com/username&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the top of the screen click the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;+&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; button at the top of the page and create a new repository. You &lt;strong&gt;MUST&lt;/strong&gt; name the repository in the following way: &lt;code&gt;username.github.io&lt;/code&gt;. Your site will not be created if it is not named correctly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we’ve got your site’s repository set up we can finally add your Jekyll files to that repository.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let’s head back to the desktop and open a new terminal window. Using the terminal navigate to the desired folder where you would like your project to be contained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, assuming you’ve got git installed we’re going to use the following command:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;    ~ $ git clone https://github.com/username/username.github.io
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now check using &lt;code&gt;ls&lt;/code&gt; or by opening up a new finder window, navigate to the same folder you just had by using the terminal and you should find a new folder by the name of &lt;code&gt;username.github.io&lt;/code&gt;. Open up this folder. This is the place where we will copy your Jekyll files to be pushed to GitHub’s servers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now assuming you’ve already built a Jekyll site, copy the files from your site into this folder. Go back to your terminal window and &lt;code&gt;cd&lt;/code&gt; into &lt;code&gt;username.github.io&lt;/code&gt; folder. Then type the following commands&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;    ~ $ git add --all
    ~ $ git commit -m &quot;Init Commit&quot;
    ~ $ git push -u origin master
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve done that, congratulations! You’ve made your first GitHub pages site! Open up a web browser and head over to &lt;code&gt;http://username.github.io&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The site should be live within a few minutes. New changes after this should be live within seconds of pushing to the server.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;an-alternative-method&quot;&gt;An Alternative Method&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you do not have git installed on your computer, or you are unfamiliar with the command line, &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; you’re running Microsoft Windows or Mac OS X, there’s another method you can use to get your site running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Download &lt;a href=&quot;https://windows.github.com/&quot;&gt;GitHub for Windows&lt;/a&gt; if you’re running Windows, or &lt;a href=&quot;https://mac.github.com/&quot;&gt;GitHub for Mac&lt;/a&gt; if you’re running OS X. Once you install GitHub’s software, login to the git client. You should see a list of your repositories within the software. Clone the repository that we just created on GitHub. There should be a menu to do this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you open a file browser, look for a folder in the location &lt;code&gt;~/username/documents/GitHub/username.github.io&lt;/code&gt;. This is the location where your repository is located. You can copy your files from the Jekyll site into that folder. Once you’ve done that, head over to the GitHub software and name your commit, add a message if you’d like. Then &lt;code&gt;commit&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;sync&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve synced your repository, you can open a web browser and navigate to &lt;code&gt;http://username.github.io&lt;/code&gt; where your site should be live in a matter of seconds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your site is not appearing, then you may have named your repository wrong, or you might have to wait a few minutes for the servers to create your site. Wait at least 10 minutes to see if your site is up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re having trouble refer to the github pages documentation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another great thing about GitHub pages is that on top of having a site for yourself, you are allowed a site for each project you have located at &lt;code&gt;http://username.github.io/project-name&lt;/code&gt;. This is a great way to host many pages and to allow people to access and learn more about your open source project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully this brief guide was enough for you to get your site set up on GitHub Pages. Good luck!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 18 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://zacblanco.github.io//blog/jekyll/hosting-with-github-pages</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://zacblanco.github.io//blog/jekyll/hosting-with-github-pages</guid>
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
        <category>site</category>
        
        <category>poole</category>
        
        <category>web</category>
        
        <category>hosting</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Adding Flavor to Jekyll</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;So you’ve got your Jekyll site running, you can write some posts, but it still doesn’t feel like your own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where Jekyll can be awesome, but also slightly confusing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the core, Jekyll takes a markdown file and uses it’s templating system called &lt;strong&gt;liquid&lt;/strong&gt; to help insert html and structure pages, and all of this is then converted into static html files that can be served on a web server.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the rest of this post I’m going to assume that you at least know how to build your site with Jekyll and serve it locally to your web browser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;liquid&quot;&gt;Liquid&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to breeze over liquid right now, but I suggest that you take a look at &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/docs/templates/&quot;&gt;the liquid templating features in Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be brief, &lt;strong&gt;liquid&lt;/strong&gt; allows us to pull sitewide variables and html code and place them right into our pages with ease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In your posts and any pages on  your Jekyll site by calling sitewide variables to insert values into your pages. In one of your posts, try adding the following.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;##### [Homepage]({{ site.url  }})
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The previous code should produce a link that directs you to your blog’s homepage. See below for it in action!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;h5 id=&quot;homepagehttpzacblancogithubio&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://zacblanco.github.io&quot;&gt;Homepage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;changing-the-style-of-your-site&quot;&gt;Changing the Style of Your Site&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll has a whole host of themes that can change the look of your site. This includes downloading and installing prebuilt themes, or diving straight in to the &lt;code&gt;sass&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;css&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;_layouts&lt;/code&gt; foldera of the site to change how it looks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sass-and-css&quot;&gt;sass and CSS&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, this sass is not the same thing that you gave to your mother when you were a teenager. Sass is a version of css that can be run through a compiler  to compile css. If you’d like to learn more about sass, &lt;a href=&quot;http://sass-lang.com/&quot;&gt;click here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take a look inside the &lt;code&gt;css&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;_sass&lt;/code&gt; folder within the directory of your jekyll site. Although these files are not &lt;code&gt;.css&lt;/code&gt; files, you can still write normal css, and if you know sass, you can write sass too. The files that you modify will change the corresponding sitewide visuals based on those files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;layouts&quot;&gt;_Layouts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;_layouts&lt;/code&gt; folder is where you can write html templates for certain types of pages on your site. There should currently be at least one layout with the name &lt;code&gt;default&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;page&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;post&lt;/code&gt;. These names are the same names you will specify in the &lt;code&gt;yaml&lt;/code&gt; at the beginning of a post, or page that you write. An example of the &lt;code&gt;yaml&lt;/code&gt; header for this page is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;    ---
    layout: post
    title: Adding Flavor to Jekyll
    tags: [jekyll, poole, site, css, web]
    ---
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can see that the layout type for this post is &lt;code&gt;post&lt;/code&gt; which tells Jekyll to use the &lt;code&gt;post.html&lt;/code&gt; layout to format and style this page. You can also edit these files to change the look of your site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;poole&quot;&gt;Poole&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally on this site I use a theme called &lt;a href=&quot;http://getpoole.com/&quot;&gt;Poole&lt;/a&gt;. If you would like to use this theme for your own site you can download and replace all of the &lt;code&gt;layout&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;css&lt;/code&gt; files with the ones from Poole. It’s a very simple and easy to use theme. Follow the documentation for the installation procedure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;wrapping-up&quot;&gt;Wrapping Up&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully from here you can better understand how Jekyll generates the site pages on your site. A bit of research and some work can make your site unique! You can also add new features and pages too by using the layouts and css files too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope now that you have enough knowledge about the structure of a Jekyll site to be able to customize it to your liking.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 17 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://zacblanco.github.io//blog/jekyll/adding-flavor-to-jekyll</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://zacblanco.github.io//blog/jekyll/adding-flavor-to-jekyll</guid>
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
        <category>poole</category>
        
        <category>site</category>
        
        <category>css</category>
        
        <category>web</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Building a Site with Jekyll</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;So I when I first started trying to make a blog I didn’t realize how difficult it would actually be to find something that worked. No other free platform contained the features that I wanted. And as a college student we should know that, free = good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; is no perfect solution, but it does provide a host of features and is much more open than any other option I could find, which is why I opted to switch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a quick intro, Jekyll straight out of the box really isn’t anything special. Basically it takes some text that you write up for your posts and converts them into some static html files that can be served to a user.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Posts are written in &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Markdown&quot;&gt;Markdown&lt;/a&gt; which is a really handy markup language. Great for writing posts, but it does have a bit of a learning curve and takes some time to get used to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another great thing about using Jekyll is that there’s quite a bit of resources, and its open source! It’s very flexible, you can use plugins, create new themes, and add commenting features. This list just goes on!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creating a site from scratch with Jekyll is definitely not for the faint-hearted. If you’re willing to put the time and effort in you can come out with a blog customized to your very liking including only the features you would like. It’s a very hands-on get-dirty-with-the-code project, but it’s a lot of fun and you might learn a few things along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of this post I’ll be showing you how exactly to install and run Jekyll to &lt;em&gt;quickly&lt;/em&gt; create your own static website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;prerequisites&quot;&gt;Prerequisites&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;please-download-ruby-first-then-rubygems&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please download ruby first, then RubyGems&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re going to need &lt;strong&gt;ruby&lt;/strong&gt; installed on your machine. If you dont have ruby installed &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ruby-lang.org/en/downloads/&quot;&gt;you can get it here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re also going to have to install &lt;a href=&quot;https://rubygems.org/pages/download&quot;&gt;RubyGems&lt;/a&gt;. It’s package manager for ruby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I’m going to assume you know how to install these or already have them on your system. Follow the documentation provided online or do a quick google search if you’re having any trouble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve got them both installed, open up a command terminal and try this command&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;~ user$ ruby --version
~ user$ gem --version
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If everything works correctly you should get some type of outputs similar to this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;ruby 2.0.0p481 (2014-05-08 revision 45883) [universal.x86_64-darwin14]
2.0.14
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Great! now we have the two essentials installed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;getting-jekyll&quot;&gt;Getting Jekyll&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a valid internet connection and a command terminal, use the following commands to install Jekyll on your machine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;~ user$ sudo gem install jekyll
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check now that you have the latest version of Jekyll installed by using&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;~ user$ jekyll --version
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;creating-your-first-site&quot;&gt;Creating your first site&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s where things start getting fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using your terminal, navigate to the chosen directory on your filesystem where you would like to keep your code, site, and any other files &lt;em&gt;(Preferably a location where you might keep some repositories)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assuming you’ve already navigated there perform the following&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;~/location/ user$ jekyll new &amp;lt;site-name&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or if you’d like to have jekyll generate the files in the folder you’re currently located in&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;~/site-name/ user$ jekyll new .
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now if you use ls command or view that directory you just created inside a file manager you should see something similar to the following&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;_config.yml	_layouts    _sass	css		index.html
_includes	_posts		about.md	feed.xml
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;configyml&quot;&gt;_config.yml&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This file is where we store some sitewide variables, like author name, baseurl, twitter and GitHub handles, etc. Edit the variables in here as you like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;posts&quot;&gt;_posts&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where you’re going to write posts in the Markdown syntax. I suggest an editor than can support previews of Markdown. Personally I use &lt;a href=&quot;http://brackets.io&quot;&gt;Adobe Brackets&lt;/a&gt; with the Markdown plugin to preview. More on all of this later&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;aboutmd&quot;&gt;about.md&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a markdown file you can edit to change the “About” page on your site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;includes-layouts-sass-css&quot;&gt;_includes, _layouts, _sass, css&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are all other places where you can change configurations and views of your site. The layout and css can all be found under these places. We’re not really going to edit those right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;making-your-first-post&quot;&gt;Making your first post&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lets navigate to our folder and create a new post. Create a new file and name is something following the scheme: &lt;code&gt;YYYY-MM-DD-your-title.md&lt;/code&gt;. Open this new file in a text editor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inside we’re going to put:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;---
layout: post
title: Hello World!
---

# Howdy there partner
Congratulations! You&#39;ve made it to[site](site.url)

We&#39;re ust getting started here.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now save your document and return to the terminal that has navigated inside of your site’s directory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;building-the-site&quot;&gt;Building the Site&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Run the following command&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;~/location/ user$ jekyll build
~/location/ user$ jekyll serve
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leave the terminal open. Open up a new tab in your browser of choice and navigate to &lt;code&gt;http://localhost:4000&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should see a home page with a link to Jekyll’s default page for new sites, and your own post we just wrote!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Click on the post to make sure it works there. If it does, congratulations! you’ve made your first blog post using Jekyll&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s tons more you can do with themes, pages, and other sweet customizations for your shiny new blog, but I’ll go into those at a later date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now, play around with Jekyll and get a feel for the software. It’s something interesting that I’ve never encountered before and is definitely worth a try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy blogging!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://zacblanco.github.io//blog/jekyll/building-a-site-with-jekyll</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://zacblanco.github.io//blog/jekyll/building-a-site-with-jekyll</guid>
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
        <category>hyde</category>
        
        <category>site</category>
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
        <category>markdown</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Updated Site</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;css-full-post-content js-full-post-content&quot;&gt;
So I just wanted to let you guys know that I&#39;ve updated my GitHub pages site. Because I like learning and building things form scratch to learn how everything is put together I built my site from the ground up and learned a few things along the way.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I was inspired to do this redesign after I came across flexbox. A CSS display property that I had not previously known of. It makes a lot of resizing and overall site layout much easier. I was inspired to rebuild my site using this.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The great thing is that flexbox is easy. It just works. and It&#39;s trivial to center things in your screen and resize the browser causing them to flow onto other line. It really is a great tool. The one caveat is that it doesn&#39;t have great browser support.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I&#39;ve currently tested on the most updated versions of the major browsers (IE, Chrome, Firefox, Safari) and so far Chrome and Firefox render the page properly. Unfortunately however, Safari definitely does not render the page properly. Most older browsers don&#39;t Although I&#39;m not too worried about this. Even with improper display the page is still navigable. IE11 surprisingly does. Even with limited support for this display I think people should start adopting it in their designs so we can force more people to upgrade their browsers, so that everyone can anjoy a modern browsing experience.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Over the next few days I&#39;ll do my best to post some simple tutorials using flexbox and some of the new CSS3 tricks I&#39;ve learned over the weekend while I made my site.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In the meantime you should check out&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;http://flexboxin5.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;flexboxin5&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;it helped me figure out what I was doing and what to include in my CSS to fix the layouts. It&#39;s a great tutorial&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Don&#39;t forget to check out the new design!&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://zacblanco.github.io/&quot;&gt;zacblanco.github.io&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Zac
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 09 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://zacblanco.github.io//blog/blogspot-posts/updated-site.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://zacblanco.github.io//blog/blogspot-posts/updated-site.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
